Anyone hear me?
有人听到我说话吗？
I can hear you.
我能听见你说话。
Thank you, alright.
谢谢，好的。
I'd like to spend today's lecture talking about threads
我想用今天的讲座来讨论一下线程，
and how xv6 does thread switching,
以及 xv6 如何进行线程切换，
this is a sort of one of the under the hood lectures about [xv6],
这是关于[xv6]的底层的讲座，
we've had lectures before about how the system calls interrupts,
我们之前讲过关于系统调用中断，
page tables and locks work
页表和锁是如何工作的，
and today we're going to talk about
今天我们将讨论
how does the xv6 switches among different processes.
xv6 是如何在不同进程之间切换的。
The reason for this the highest level reason for this is
最高层次的原因是，
that people like their computer to be able to
因为人们喜欢他们的电脑能够
do more than one task at the same time,
同时完成多项任务，
so the reason might be that you're supporting time sharing,
所以原因可能是支持分时，
like Athena allows many users to login at the same time
像 Athena 一样，允许多个用户同时登录，
and you know they call run processes
它们都可以运行进程，
or even a single user machine
甚至是一台单用户机器，
or even your iPhone,
甚至是你的 iPhone ，
you may run many different processes
你可以运行许多不同的进程，
and expect the computer to do all the things you ask of it,
并期望计算机能做你要求它做的所有事情，
not just one thing.
而不只是一件事。
Another reason that people like to support multiple tasks is
人们喜欢支持多任务的另一个原因是，
because it can ease program structure,
因为它可以简化程序结构，
threads in particular today's topic,
特别是今天的话题线程，
are sometimes used as a way to help people,
有时作为一种方式来帮助人们，
to help programmers put together a program in a sort of simple elegant way,
帮助程序员以一种简单优雅的方式把程序组合在一起，
to reduce complexity,
以降低复杂性，
and you actually saw an example of this
实际上你已经看到了这样的例子，
in the first lab with the prime number sieve,
在第一个实验中的素数筛子，
which didn't use threads exactly but use multiple processes,
它不使用线程，但使用多个进程，
in order to help structure this your prime number sieve software
为了帮助构建素数筛选软件，
and arguably it's sort of a more convenient or elegant or simpler way
这是一种更方便、更优雅或更简单的方式，
to to write that software.
去写那个软件。
And the final reason why people use threads is,
人们使用线程的最后一个原因是，
to get parallel speedup from multi core machines,
为了从多核机器获得并行加速，
so it's common to break up your program
所以分解你的程序是很常见的，
in a way that using threads
使用线程的方式，
to allow different parts of the same program to run on different cores,
允许同一程序的不同部分在不同的内核上运行，
and if you can, maybe if you're lucky,
也许如果你幸运的话，
if you can split your program up to run on four threads on four cores,
你可以把程序拆分为四个线程运行在四个核心上，
you might be able to get a factor of four speedup how fast it runs.
你也许可以把它的速度提高到原来的四倍。
And indeed, you can view the xv6 kernel as a multi-core parallel program.
实际上，你可以将 xv6 内核视为一个多核并行程序。
So what threads are,
那么线程是什么，
is an abstraction to simplify programming,
是一种简化编程的抽象，
when you have many tasks,
当你有很多任务时，
when you want to juggle many tasks,
当你想要同时处理多项任务时，
so what a thread is is,
所以线程是什么，
you can think of a thread as just being a single serial execution,
你可以把线程想成一个单一的串行执行，
if you just write a program that does one thing after another,
如果你写一个程序做一件又一件事情，
and you run that program,
你运行这个程序，
that you know you can view the program as a sort of single thread of control.
你可以把这个程序看作是一种单一的控制线程。
So, this is a loose definition.
所以，这是一个宽泛的定义。
Because there's many different sort of flavors of what people mean by threads,
因为，人们所说的线程有多种不同的定义，
but we'll say it's one serial execution,
但我们说这是一个串行执行，
so it's what you get if you fire up one CPU
因此，如果你启动一个 CPU ，
and have it you know just execute one instruction after another in the ordinary way.
让它用普通的方式一条接一条地执行指令。
We often talk about thread having state,
我们经常谈到线程有状态，
because it's going to turn out,
因为结果是，
we're going to want to save away thread state
我们想要保存线程状态，
and restore it later,
之后再恢复它，
and so the right way to think about thread state,
所以思考线程状态的正确方式是，
for the most part,
最重要的部分，
the most important part perhaps of the thread state is its program counter,
最重要的线程状态的可能是程序计数器，
because it's an execution,
因为它是执行，
we care a lot about where is it in its execution
我们很关心它在执行中的什么位置，
and what address is it executing instructions,
它执行指令的地址是什么，
but also we care about the rest of the microprocessor state,
但我们也关心微处理器的其它状态，
that's required to support this execution
这是支持执行所必需的，
and so that means it's.
所以这意味着它是。
The state of a thread includes the registers that the compiler uses to hold variables
线程状态包括编译器用来保存变量的寄存器，
and also because the just the way the compiler generates code,
还因为编译器生成代码的方式，
thread state includes a stack,
线程状态包括堆栈，
so typically each thread has its own stack
所以，一般每个线程都有自己的堆栈，
dedicated to executing that thread,
专用于执行该线程，
and the stack records, the record of function calls,
堆栈记录函数调用的记录，
that the reflect the current point in the execution of that thread.
反映该线程执行中的当前点。
And so what a threading system xv6 includes a threading system inside it,
所以， xv6 在其内部包括线程系统，
what a threading system does is
线程系统的所做的是，
manage this interleave, automate the interleaving of multiple threads,
自动执行多个交织的线程，
you would like to be able to fire up two or 400 or a thousand threads
你可能希望启动 200 或 400 或 1000 个线程，
and the threading system figure out how to juggle all those threads
线程系统会处理所有这些线程，
and cause them all to make [progress] and all to execute.
使它们全部发展，全部执行。
There's really two main strategy,
有两个主要的策略，
so we want to [interleave],
我们想要交错，
this is gonna be big topic here,
这是一个很大的话题，
how to interleave threads, many threads,
如何交错多个线程，
one way to interleave the execution of many threads is
交错执行多个线程的一种方法是
to have multiple CPUs,
拥有多个 CPU ，
maybe as on a multi-core processor
像是在多核处理器上，
and then each CPU can run its own thread,
然后每个 CPU 可以运行自己的线程，
so if you have four CPUs,
所以如果你有 4 个 CPU ，
there's an obvious way to run four threads,
很明显可以运行 4 个线程，
to run one thread per CPU,
每个 CPU 上运行一个线程，
and then each thread automatically gets its own program counter registers,
然后每个线程自动获得自己的程序计数器寄存器，
that is the program counter register is associated with the CPU is running on,
程序计数器寄存器是与正在运行的 CPU 关联的，
but if you have four CPUs and you have a thousand threads,
但是如果你有 4 个 CPU 和上千个线程，
then you know how using one core of thread,
那么如何在核心上使用线程，
is not going to be enough of an answer.
不是一个好回答的问题。
And so the other main strategy that we'll see,
所以，我们看到的另一个主要策略是，
indeed the topic of most of this lecture is
实际上，这节课的大部分内容都是，
how each CPU is going to switch among different threads,
每个 CPU 如何在不同线程之间切换，
so if I have one CPU and a thousand threads,
所以，如果我有一个 CPU 和上千个线程，
we're going to see how xv6 builds switching system,
我们看看 xv6 是如何构建切换系统的，
that allows xv6 to run one thread for a while
这允许 xv6 在一段时间内运行一个线程，
and then switch and set aside
然后切换并放在一边，
and save the state of that one thread
保存该线程的状态，
and switch to executing a second thread for a while
并切换到第二个线程，执行一段时间，
and then a third thread and so forth,
然后是第三个线程，等等，
until it's executed a little bit of each thread,
直到它执行了每个线程的一部分，
and then go back and execute more of the of the first thread and so on.
然后，返回到第一个线程并继续执行，等等。
And indeed, xv6 like most operating system,
实际上， xv6 和大多数操作系统，
[] the xv6 will run threads on all the cores that are available
xv6 在所有可用核心上运行线程，
and each core will switch among threads,
并且每个核心在线程之间切换，
because there's typical typically, although not always,
因为通常是，尽管并非总是如此，
there's typically many more threads than there are CPUs.
线程数通常比 CPU 数多得多。
One of the many ways in which different threading systems
一个线程系统的不同之处，
or instances of threading systems differ is
或者线程系统实例的不同之处是，
in whether or not they share memory.
是它们否共享内存。
So this is important point.
所以这是很重要一点。
One possibility is that you could have a single address space,
一种可能是，你可以有一个单独的地址空间，
with many threads executing in that address space
许多线程在该地址空间中执行，
and then they see each other's changes,
它们可以看到彼此的变动，
if one of the threads sharing some memory modifies variable,
如果共享内存的一个线程修改了变量，
then the other thread sharing that memory will see the modification.
那么其它共享该内存的线程会看到修改。
And so it's in the context of threads running and sharing memory
所以，在线程共享内存的情况下，
that we need things like the locks
我们需要锁，
that you saw in the last lecture.
你在上一节课上看到的。
Xv6 kernel is shared memory,
xv6 内核是共享内存的，
so xv6, there's,
所以 xv6 有，
xv6 has, supports the [notion] of kernel threads,
xv6 支持内核线程的概念，
there's one kernel thread per process
每个进程有一个内核线程，
that executes system calls for that process,
来执行该进程的系统调用，
all those kernel threads share kernel memory,
所有这些内核线程共享内核内存，
so xv6 kernel threads do share memory.
所以 xv6 内核线程共享内存。
And on the other hand,
另一方面，
xv6 has another kind of threads,
xv6 还有另一种线程，
each user process essentially has a single thread of control,
每个用户进程都有一个控制线程，
that executes the user instructions for that process,
执行该进程的用户指令，
and indeed a lot of the xv6 kernel threading machinery is
实际上， xv6 内核线程机制的一大部分是
automatically in support of being able to support and switch them on many user processes,
支持自动地在多个用户进程之间切换，
each user process has a memory
每个用户进程具有内存，
and a single thread that runs in that memory,
单个线程在其中运行，
so xv6 user processes,
所以 xv6 用户进程，
each process has one thread
每个进程有一个线程，
and so there's no sharing of memory among threads within a single xv6 user process,
所以在单个 xv6 用户进程内的线程之间不会共享内存，
because you get multiple processes,
因为你有多个进程，
but each of those processes is an address space with a single thread,
但是每个进程都是一个地址空间和单个线程，
the processes in xv6 don't share memory.
在 xv6 中的进程步共享内存。
In other more sophisticated operating systems,
在其它更复杂的操作系统中，
for example Linux,
比如，在 Linux 中，
Linux user level does allow multiple threads in a process
Linux 用户级允许在一个进程中有多个线程，
and the processes and those threads share the memory of that single process
并且这些线程共享那个单个进程的内存，
and that's super cool if you want to write user level programs
这非常酷，如果你想编写用户级的程序，
that user level parallel programs that get speed up from multiple cores
用户级并行程序可以使用多核提速，
better requires sort of another,
需要另一种，
it uses a lot of the same basic techniques,
它使用了很多相同的基础技术，
we're going to talk about today,
我们今天要讨论的，
but there's a certain amount more sophistication in Linux to get it,
但是，在 Linux 实现它有一定的复杂度，
keep track of multiple threads per process instead of just one.
跟踪每个进程的多个线程，而不只是一个。
Okay, at a sort of high level, I just want to mention,
好的，从高层次上，我想提一下，
that there's other ways
还有其他方法，
to support the interleaving of multiple tasks on a single computer
可以支持在一台计算机上交错执行多个任务，
and we're not going to talk about them,
我们不会讨论它们，
if you're curious you can look up things like event-driven programming
如果你好奇，可以看看事件驱动编程的东西，
or state machines
或者状态机，
and these are non-thread techniques
它们是非线程技术，
to share one computer among many different tasks,
在许多不同任务之间共享一台计算机，
it turns out you know sort of on the spectrum of different schemes
这些是不同层次的不同方案，
for supporting multiple tasks on a computer,
为了支持计算机上的多任务，
threads are not very efficient,
线程效率不是很高，
there's a more efficient schemes,
有更有效的方案，
but threads are usually the most convenient way,
但是线程通常是最方便的方式，
most programmer friendly way,
最适合程序员的方式，
to support lots of different tasks.
来支持许多不同的任务。
Okay, there's a couple of challenges,
好的，这里有几个挑战，
that we're gonna have to bite off,
我们必须解决，
if we want to implement a threading system.
如果我们要实现线程系统。
The, so this is just high level challenges.
所以这是高级别的挑战。
One is as I mentioned before,
一个是我之前提到的，
how to actually implement the switching for interleave,
如何实现交错（线程）的切换，
the switching that allows us to interleave the execution of multiple threads,
这个切换允许我们交错执行多个线程，
and this sort of broad name for this process of switching deciding,
这个进程的切换决定有一个广义名称，
or going to leave off one thread and start executing another thread,
离开一个线程，并执行另一个线程，
it's often called scheduling.
这通常称为调度。
And we'll see that xv6 [] as an actual piece of code,
我们将看到 xv6 []的一段代码，
that's the scheduler,
就是调度器，
indeed has multiple schedulers one per core,
实际上，有多个调度器，每个核心一个，
but the general idea of how do you drive,
但是关于如何驱动，
the decision to switch from one to another,
如何决定从一个切换到另一个，
how to pick the next thread to run,
如何选择要运行的下一个线程，
its called scheduling.
这就是调度。
Another question is,
另一个问题是，
if you want to actually implement the switch from one thread to another,
如果你想实现从一个线程到另一个线程的切换，
you need to save and restore,
你需要保存和恢复，
so we need to decide what needs to be saved
所以我们需要决定，需要保存什么，
and where to save it,
保存到哪，
when, it needs to be saved when we leave off executing one thread
当我们离开一个线程时，需要保存它，
and restored when we want to resume executing that thread at some later time,
并在稍后想要重新执行该线程时，恢复它，
and final question is what to do about compute bound threads.
最后一个问题是，如何处理计算密集型线程。
The, many of the options,
很多选择，
many of the most straightforward options for thread switching
很多切换线程的直接的选择，
involve the threads are voluntarily saying
引入线程自愿表示，
well I'm going to save away my state
我要保存自己的状态，
and sort of run another, let another thread be run,
让另一个线程运行，
but what do we have a user program that's doing some long running calculation,
但是，如果我们有一个用户程序做长时间的计算，
that might take hours,
可能需要几个小时，
it's not going to be particularly thinking about,
它不会特别考虑，
oh now be time to good time to let something else run,
现在是时候让别的线程运行了，
so it's most convenient to have some way of
所以最方便是，通过某种方式
sort of automatically revoking control from some long running compute bound process,
自动从长时间运行的计算密集型进程收回控制权，
setting it aside and maybe running it later.
把它放在一边，之后再运行。
Alright, so I'm going to talk about these,
好的，我要谈谈这些，
I'm actually going to talk about
实际上，首先我要谈谈，
the machinery for dealing with compute bound threads first.
处理计算密集型线程的机制。
And, scheme for that is something you've come up before,
而且，方案就是你以前知道的，
that's timer interrupts.
那就是定时器中断。
And the idea here is that,
这里的想法是，
there's a, a piece of hardware on each CPU on each core,
每个核心，每个 CPU 上都有一个硬件，
that generates periodic interrupts,
它会产生周期性的中断，
and the xv6 or any operating system
而 xv6 或任何操作系统
really arranges to have those interrupts delivered to the kernel,
将这些中断传送给内核，
so even if we're running at user level at some loop
所以，即使我们在用户级运行一些循环，
that's you know computing the first billion digits of pi,
比如计算 pi 的前 10 亿位，
nevertheless the timer interrupts go off at some point
尽管如此，定时器中断还是会在某个时间点发生，
maybe every ten milliseconds
可能是每 10 毫秒一次，
and transfer control from that user level code
将控制从该用户级代码转移到
into the interrupt handler in the kernel,
内核中的中断处理程序，
and so that's the first step in the kernel being able to gain control
这是内核获得控制权的第一步，
to switch among different user level processes, user level threads,
用来在不同的用户级线程之间切换，
even if those user level threads aren't cooperative.
即使那些用户级线程不是协作的。
And the basic scheme is that in the interrupt handler,
基本方案是，在中断处理器中，
so we're gonna have you know kernel handler for these interrupts.
所以我们有处理这些程序的内核中断。
And we'll see,
我们会看到，
that the kernel handler yields,
内核处理程序让出，
this is the sort of name for this it yields,
这个名称是 yields ，
the kernel handler sort of voluntarily yields the CPU back to the scheduler
内核处理程序自愿让出 CPU 给调度器，
it tell the scheduler look, you can let something else run now.
告诉调度器，你现在可以运行其他线程。
And this yields is really a form of thread switch,
而这个让出是一种线程切换的形式，
that saves away the state of the current thread,
它保存了当前线程的状态，
so it can be restored later.
这样以后就可以恢复。
And we'll see the full story here,
我们会在这里看到整个流程，
actually you've seen a lot of the full story here,
实际上，你已经在这里看到了整个流程，
because it involves an interrupt,
因为它涉及到中断，
what you already know about the full story some complex,
你已经知道整个流程有些复杂，
but the basic idea is that a timer interrupt
但是基本的想法是定时器中断
gives control to the kernel
将控制权交给内核，
and the kernel voluntarily yields the CPU,
而内核自愿让出 CPU ，
this is called as a piece of terminology preemptive scheduling.
这个术语称为抢占调度。
And what that means is that,
它的意思是，
the preemptive means is that,
抢占的意思是，
even if the code that's running doesn't, you know doesn't want to,
即使正在运行的代码不愿意，
you know doesn't explicitly yield the CPU,
没有明确地让出 CPU ，
the timer interrupt is going to take control away
定时器中断会夺走控制权，
and we're going to yield for it
我们会让出给它，
and the opposite of preemptive scheduling might be called maybe voluntary scheduling.
抢占式调度的反义词称为自愿式调度。
And the interesting thing is that
有趣的事情是，
the the implementation in xv6 and other operating systems of preemptive scheduling is
抢占式调度在 xv6 等操作系统中的实现是
this timer interrupt forcibly takes away the CPU
定时器中断强制夺取 CPU ，
and then the kernel basically does a voluntary yield
然后内核自愿让出，
thread thread switch on [have] of that process.
切换到那个进程的线程。
Now, another just piece of terminology that comes up here is
这里出现的另一个术语是，
that while the threads running,
当线程运行时，
there's need to distinguish,
有必要区分，
systems that distinguish between threads that are currently actually running on some CPU
系统区分当前在某些 CPU 上运行的线程，
versus threads that would like to run, but aren't currently running on any CPU,
与想要运行，但当前没有在任何 CPU 上运行的线程，
but you know could run if a CPU became free
但是如果 CPU 空闲就可以运行，
versus threads that actually don't want to run,
与那些实际上不想运行的线程，
because they're waiting for IO
因为它们在等待 IO ，
or waiting for some event.
或者在等待什么事件。
And [] this distinction is often called state,
这种区别通常称为状态，
even though the full state of the thread is
即使线程的完整状态
actually much more complicated than that.
要比这复杂得多。
Since this is going to come up,
既然说到这件事，
I just want a list out a couple of states that will be seeing,
我想列出几个我们会看到的状态，
and these are states that xv6 maintains,
这些是 xv6 管理的状态，
there's a state called RUNNING,
有一种状态是 RUNNING ，
which means it's actually executing on some core, some CPU right now,
意味着它正在某个 CPU 上运行，
there's RUNNABLE, which means not currently executing anywhere,
有 RUNNABLE ，意味着目前没有在任何地方运行，
but just a saved state, but would like to run as soon as possible
但是有保存的状态，想要尽快运行，
and then it turns out there's a state,
然后还有一个状态，
which won't come out much today, but will come up next week,
今天不会讲太多，但是下周会讲到，
called SLEEPING, just means the threads waiting for some IO event
叫做 SLEEPING ，表示线程等待某个 IO 事件，
and only wants to run after the IO event occurs,
只有在 IO 事件发生之后运行，
so today we're mostly concerned with running and runnable threads
所以今天我们关注的运行时和可运行线程，
and what this preemptive switch does,
这个抢先切换所做的，
what this timer interrupt does and the yield is
这个定时器中断和 yield 所做的是，
basically convert a running thread
将一个运行时线程，
whatever thread was interrupted by the timer
即被定时器中断的线程，
into a runnable thread.
转换为一个可运行线程。
That is a thread,
这是一个线程，
that's by yielding or converting that thread into a thread,
通过让出或转换为另一个线程，
that's not running right now,
它现在没有运行，
but would actually like to clearly,
但很明显它将会运行，
because it was running at the timer timer interrupt.
因为它在计时器中断时运行。
Okay so,
好的，那么，
running thread its program counter registers are actually in the CPU,
运行的线程的程序计数器寄存器在 CPU 中，
you know in the hardware registers of the CPU that's executing it,
在执行它的 CPU 的硬件寄存器中，
a runnable thread though has no,
可运行线程没有，
it's now doesn't have a CPU associated with it
它现在没有关联的 CPU ，
and therefore we need to save,
所以，我们需要保存，
for every runnable state, we need to save whatever CPU state,
对于可运行状态，我们需要保存所有 CPU 状态，
whatever state the CPU was keeping when that thread was running,
任何线程运行时的 CPU 使用的状态，
so we need to copy the CPU contents,
所以我们需要复制 CPU 的内容，
you know which is not RAM, but just registers really,
不是 RAM ，只是寄存器，
from the CPU into memory somewhere to save them,
从 CPU 到内存中的某个地方以保存它们，
when we turn to thread from running to runnable.
当我们将线程从运行时转为可运行的时候。
And again this is the basically the state we have to explicitly save yours,
再说一次，我们必须明确保存的状态，
just the state, the executing state of the CPU,
只有 CPU 的运行状态，
which is the program counter and registers at CPU,
也就是程序计数器和 CPU 寄存器，
so these need to be saved,
所以这些需要保存，
only convert a thread to runnable.
当将线程转换为可运行的。
When some scheduler finally decides to run a runnable thread,
当某个调度器决定运行可运行线程时，
then as part of the many steps in getting that thread going again and resuming it,
那么，作为再次运行该线程的步骤一部分，
we're going to see that the program counter,
我们会看到程序计数器，
the saved program counter registers are copied back into the CPUs,
保存的程序计数器寄存器被复制回 CPU ，
actual register on the CPU that the scheduler decides to run it on.
到调度器决定运行线程的 CPU 的寄存器上。
Alright, any questions about these terminology?
好的，关于这些术语有什么问题吗？
Alright, I'm gonna,
好的，我要，
now sort of talk about a sort of more xv6 [] view of things.
现在讨论一下 xv6 的东西。
I'm gonna draw two pictures,
我要画两张图，
really of threads and xv6
关于线程和 xv6 ，
are kind of simplified picture and a more detailed picture.
一张是简单图，一张是更详细的图。
So as usually the user stuff up here
像往常一样，用户的东西在上面，
and the kernel down here.
内核在下面。
We might be running multiple processes at user level,
我们可能在用户级别运行多个进程，
maybe you know the C compiler and ls and shell,
也许是 C 编译器、 ls 和 shell ，
they may or may not be all wanting to run at the same time,
它们可能同时或不同时运行，
at user level, each of these processes has,
在用户级别，每个进程都有，
you know it has memory,
它有内存，
and of particular interest to us,
我们特别感兴趣的是，
each of these processes has a user stack,
每个进程都有用户堆栈，
and while it's running it has registers in the RISC-V hardware,
当它运行时，它在 RISC-V 硬件中有寄存器，
so PC plus registers.
PC 和寄存器。
Alright, so while programs running,
好的，当程序运行时，
you know there's essentially a thread of control that's running at user level
有一个在用户级别运行的控制线程，
and the way I'm going to talk about it is,
我要说的是，
as if there's a user thread,
就像有一个用户线程，
that consists of the user stack, user memory, user program counter, user registers,
包含用户堆栈，用户内存，用户程序计数器，用户寄存器，
if the program makes a system call,
如果程序访问系统调用，
interrupted and goes into the kernel,
中断并进入内核，
then this stuff saved away in this program's trapframe
然后这些东西保存在这个程序的 trapframe 中，
and a kernel, the kernel thread for this program is activated
并且这个程序的内核线程被激活，
and so now this is the trapframe hold saved user stuff
现在， trapframe 保存着用户的东西，
after we saved a way the user [] program counter registers,
在我们保存了用户程序计数器寄存器之后，
then we switch the CPU to using the kernel stack.
然后，我们将 CPU 切换到使用内核堆栈。
And you know we don't need to restore registers,
我们不需要恢复寄存器，
because, through the the kernel thread for process isn't really running,
因为，进程的内核线程并没有真正运行，
it has no real save state, when the user thread is running
当用户线程运行时，它没有实际的保存状态，
instead it's sort of the kernel thread is kind of activated on its stack.
相反的，内核线程在其堆栈上激活。
So the first time in in the trampoline and a user trap code.
所以，第一次在 trampoline 和用户 trap 代码。
And then the kernel runs for a while,
然后内核运行一段时间，
maybe running a system call or interrupt handler,
也许是系统调用或中断处理程序，
whatever it maybe,
不管是什么，
and sometimes it is a system call particular will just simply return,
有时，系统调用只是简单地返回，
from this point back to the same process
从这里到同一个进程，
and return to user space or restore this program's program counter registers,
返回到用户空间，或者恢复该程序的程序计数器寄存器，
but it could also be that instead of simply returning,
但也可能不是简单地返回，
for one reason or another,
而是因为这样或那样的原因，
maybe because it was a timer interrupt,
可能是因为定时器中断，
we're actually going to switch to another process
我们要切换到另一个进程，
and the very high-level view of that is that
高层次的观点是，
if the xv6 scheduler decides switch from this process to a different process,
如果 xv6 调度器决定从这个进程切换到不同进程，
what the first thing that really happens is
发生的第一件事是，
that we're going to switch kernel threads
我们要切换内核线程，
from this processe's kernel thread to the other process's kernel thread,
从这个进程的内核线程到另一个进程的内核线程，
and then the other processes kernel thread will return back to user space.
然后其他进程的内核线程返回到用户空间。
So supposing that the C compiler [] needs to read the disk
所以，假设 C 编译器需要读取磁盘，
and so it's going to yield the CPU
所以它会让出 CPU ，
while sleeping to wait for the disk to complete,
休眠并等待磁盘完成，
maybe ls wants to execute and is in runnable state,
也许 ls 想要执行，并处于可运行状态，
what the xv6 scheduler maybe they do is that,
xv6 调度器可能做的是，
well, if ls is in runnable state,
如果 ls 处于可运行状态，
that means it left off somewhere
意味着它在某个地方停了下来，
and its state was saved away possibly by a timer interrupt
它的状态保存在一边，可能是因为定时器中断，
and so ls will actually have a saved trapframe
所以 ls 有一个保存的 traframe ，
with user registers and its own kernel stack,
包含用户寄存器和它自己的内核堆栈，
and as it turns out save set of kernel registers associated with the kernel thread
它保存了一些与内核线程有关的寄存器，
which is going to be called the context.
这被称为上下文。
So, if xv6 switches from the compiler kernel thread to ls's kernel thread,
所以，如果 xv6 从编译器内核线程切换到 ls 内核线程，
xv6 will save away the kernel registers,
xv6 将保存内核寄存器，
in a context with a C the compilers kernel thread switch to the ls thread,
在 C 编译器内核线程切换到 ls 线程的上下文中，
complex scheme which I'll describe a little bit later,
这个复杂的方案，我稍后会描述，
we'll restore ls's kernel thread registers
我们恢复 ls 的内核线程寄存器，
from the previously save context from one ls last left off,
从上一次停止的 ls 上下文中，
maybe ls will finish whatever system call was executing,
也许 ls 完成正在执行的系统调用，
you know on the ls's kernel thread stack,
在 ls 的内核线程堆栈上，
and then return back to ls system call,
然后返回到 ls 系统调用，
on the way to return to user space
在返回用户空间的路上，
that will restore these previously saved user registers for ls
它将为 ls 恢复以前保存的用户寄存器，
and then resume executing ls.
然后继续执行 ls 。
So, there's bunch of details here which we'll talk about,
所以，这里有一堆我们将要讨论的细节，
but maybe the main point here is that
但也许这里的重点是，
we never in xv6 see direct user to user context switches,
在 xv6 中，我们不会看到用户到用户的上下文切换，
when we're switching from one process to another,
当我们从一个进程切换到另一个进程，
always the sort of strategy
总是一种策略，
by which xv6 switches from executing one process to another process is
xv6 从一个进程切换到另一个进程是，
you jump in the kernel, saves the process state,
跳入内核，保存进程状态，
run this process's kernel thread switch to the kernel thread of another process,
从这个进程的内核线程切换到另一个进程的内核线程，
that suspended itself
那个进程暂停了自己，
and then return and restore user register,
然后返回并恢复用户寄存器，
so it's always this indirect strategy,
所以一直是这种间接的策略，
actually even more indirect than this,
实际上比这更间接的，
to threads swhich,
对于线程切换，
where the net effect is to switch from one user process to another user process.
实际结果是从一个用户进程切换到另一个用户进程。
Question about this diagram or anything?
关于这张图，有什么问题吗？
Switched the scheduler, that happens in between those two, right.
切换，调度器，发生在这两个之间，对吗。
Yep, all right, let me talk about the scheduler,
是的，好的，让我来谈谈调度器，
so the real picture is actually a significantly more complex than that.
实际图片要比这复杂得多。
This is a may or more, gonna be more full diagram,
这是更完整的图，
let's say we have process one which is executing,
假设我们有进程一 P1 正在运行，
and process two which is runnable, but not currently running,
而进程二 P2 是可运行的，但是现在没有运行，
now the additional layer of details,
还有一些额外的细节，
we actually have multiple cores in xv6,
我们在 xv6 中有多个核心，
let's say we have two cores,
假设我们有两个核心，
so that means that at the hardware level,
这意味着在硬件层面上，
we have CPU0 which is one of the cores
我们有 CPU0 ，它是其中一个核心，
and let's say CPU1.
还有 CPU1 。
And the more full story about
更完整的故事是
how we get from executing user space to,
我们如何从执行用户空间到，
in one process executing in user space
在用户空间中执行的一个进程，
in another runnable but not yet running process,
到另一个可运行但没有运行的进程，
the first part is about the same as I talked about
第一部分与我所说的相同，
and may say a timer interrupt forces
定时器中断强制
transfer control from the user process into the kernel,
将控制从用户进程转移到内核，
the trampoline code saves the user registers and trapframe for process one,
trampoline 代码保存进程一的用户寄存器和 trapframe ，
and then executes usertrap
然后执行 usertrap ，
which figures out what to do with this trap or interrupt,
它知道该怎么处理这个 trap 或中断，
you know system call, let's say as a,
系统调用，比如，
so for a little while, we're executing ordinary kernel C code,
所以有段时间，我们执行普通的内核 C 代码，
on the kernel stack of process one.
在进程一的内核堆栈上。
Let's say process one, the kernel code process once decides it wants to yield the CPU,
假设，进程一的内核代码决定让出 CPU ，
it has a bunch of things, which we'll see the details of,
它有一堆东西，我们可以看到细节，
that end up in a call to this routine switch,
最终调用这个例程切换，
just sort of one of the central routines in this story,
是这个故事中的一个中心例程，
switch saves away this context,
switch 保存上下文，
that registers for the kernel thread that's running in context one,
在上下文一中运行的内核线程的寄存器，
so there's two sets of registers,
所以有两组用户寄存器，
the user registers, the trapframe, the kernel thread registers in the context.
用户寄存器， trapframe ，内核线程寄存器在上下文中。
Switch doesn't actually,
switch 不会，
switch switches from one content from one thread to another,
switch 从一个线程切换到另一个，
but in fact the way xv6 is designed,
但是实际上 xv6 的设计方式，
the only place that a user thread,
用户线程，
sorry, the kernel thread running on a CPU can switch to is
抱歉，在 CPU 上运行的内核线程可以切换的唯一位置是，
what's called the scheduler thread for that CPU.
那个 CPU 的调度器线程。
So we can't even switch directly to another process,
所以我们甚至不能直接切换到另一个进程，
can only switch to the scheduler thread,
只能切换到调度器线程，
so there's a,
所以这里有一个，
the complete thread apparatus dedicated to the scheduler for CPU0,
完整的线程装置专用于 CPU0 的调度器，
since we're running on CPUs,
因为我们使用的是 CPU ，
this switch is going to switch to the previously saved registers for the scheduler thread,
这个 switch 会切换到调度器线程的之前保存的寄存器，
so let's say schedule zero.
假设是调度器 0 。
And in the scheduler for CPU0,
在 CPU0 的调度器中，
switch will, by restoring these registers,
switch 会，通过恢复这些寄存器，
since registers include the stack pointer,
由于寄存器包括堆栈指针，
the return from switch as we see,
正如我们看到的， switch 的返回，
will now actually return up to the scheduler function on CPU,
将会返回到 CPU0 上的调度器函数，
and scheduler function will do some cleanup
调度器函数会进行一些清理，
to finish putting process one to sleep,
使进程一进入休眠状态，
then it'll look in the process table for another process,
然后它在进程表中查找另一个进程，
a runnable process,
一个可运行进程，
and if it finds one,
如果它找到了一个，
and so we've sort of gone down here and up into the scheduler,
所以我们从这里下来，然后到调度器，
if the scheduler finds another process to run
如果调度器找到另一个要运行的进程，
or even finds process one is runnable and still wants to run,
或者发现进程一是可运行的，并且仍然想要运行，
find process one nothing else nothing else wants to run,
找到进程一，没有别的进程想要运行，
but in any case, the scheduler will call switch again,
但不管怎样，调度器会再次调用 switch ，
to switch contexts to say process two,
将上下文切换到进程二，
in the process switch will save its own registers again in its own context,
在线程中， switch 再次保存自己的寄存器到自己的上下文中，
they'll be a previously saved context too,
它们也会是前序保存的上下文，
from whenever process two left off
当进程而停止时，
that those this set of registers will be restored,
这组寄存器将被恢复，
process two will have made a previous call,
进程二将使用前序调用，
to switch, to switch to the scheduler thread just like process one did
像进程一样，切换到调度器线程，
when it left off,
当它停下来的时候，
that called a switch return to,
它调用 switch 返回
whatever system call or interrupt,
无论系统调用还是中断，
process two is end, when that's finished,
进程二结束，
there will be a previously saved trapframe for process two,
会有一个先前保存的进程二的 trapframe ，
that will contain user registers,
它将包含用户寄存器，
also be restored or return back up into user space.
也可以恢复或返回到用户空间。
And there's a complete, a separate scheduler thread for each CPU,
每个 CPU 都有一个完整的、单独的调度器线程，
so, they'll also be saved,
所以，它们也将被保存，
context for the scheduler thread for CPU,
CPU1 的调度器线程的上下文，
and a scheduler loop running on scheduler one
以及在调度器一上运行的调度器循环，
and whatever process, you know process three or something is running on CPU one
以及任何运行在 CPU1 上的进程，比如进程三或其他，
when it decides to give up the CPU,
当它决定让出 CPU 时，
it'll switch into scheduler thread for it for its CPU.
它将切换到 CPU 为它的调度器线程。
Alright, there's a question,
好的，这里有一个问题，
where the context stored,
上下文存储在哪里，
it turns out that for the operations I've been talking about,
对于这些我刚才说的操作，
the saved,
保存的，
in fact always the for a thread switch,
事实上，对于线程切换，
these contexts, these saved register sets for kernel threads,
这些上下文，这些内核线程保存的寄存器
all in the process structure,
都在进程结构体中，
so any given kernel thread can only have one set of saved kernel registers.
所以，任何内核线程只能有一组保存的内核寄存器。
Because each thread is only executing a single place
因为每个线程只在一个位置执行，
and its context kind of reflects that place that it was executing on it left off
它的上下文在某种程度上反映了它执行的位置，
a thread is a single thread of control,
线程是单个控制线程，
so a thread really only needs one context for registers,
所以一个线程只需要一个寄存器的上下文，
so it's in the process structures p arrow, p->context.
所以，它在进程结构体的 p->context 。
And the scheduler, each scheduler thread has its own context
而且每个调度器线程都有自己的上下文，
which actually not in the,
不是在，
there's no process associated with this scheduler thread,
没有与调度器线程关联的进程，
this is actually scheduler's context is stored in the struct CPU for that core.
调度器的上下文存储在核心的 CPU 结构体中。
There's an array of these CPU's struct one per core,
有一组 CPU 结构体，每个核心一个，
each one has a context.
每一个有一个上下文。
Question, why can't we include the registers in the trapframe for the process,
为什么我们不能将寄存器包括在进程的 trapframe 中，
that is, you know actually the those registers could be stored in the trapframe
实际上，这些寄存器可以存储在 trapframe 中，
which may, because there's only one save set of kernel thread registers,
因为只有一个内核线程寄存器的存储集，
for process, we could save them in any data structure
对于进程，我们可以将它们保存在任何数据结构中，
for which there's one element of instance of that data structure process,
比如存在进程数据结构实例的一个元素，
there's one struct process,
只有一个进程结构，
there's one struct trapframe for process,
有一个用于进程的 trapframe 结构，
we could store the registers in the trapframe.
我们可以把寄存器保存在 trapframe 中。
I mean just sort of for,
我是说，只是，
maybe simplicity or clarity of code,
可能是为了代码的简单性或清晰性，
the trapframe I think, entirely consists of data,
trapframe 只包含数据，
that's needed when entering and leaving the kernel.
进入和离开内核时需要的（数据）。
And the struct context is consists of the stuff that needs to be saved and restored,
content 结构由需要保存和恢复的内容组成，
when switching to and from between the kernel thread and the scheduler thread.
当内核线程和调度器线程之间切换时。
Okay, question is,
好的，问题是，
yield something that's called by the user of the kernel, called by the kernel,
yield 是有内核调用的，
so the user threads, there's not really a direct way in xv6
所以在 xv6 中，用户线程没有真正直接的方式，
for user threads to talk about, yielding the CPU or switching,
用户线程让出 CPU 或切换，
that it's done by the kernel kind of transparently,
它是通过内核这种透明的完成，
you know it points in time when the kernel feels that it needs to happen,
它会在内核觉得有必要发生的时候出现，
if there are threads,
如果有线程，
there are sometimes when, you can sort of guess
有时候，你能猜到，
that probably a certain system call will result in yield,
一个系统调用可能让出，
like if a process does a read on a pipe,
比如，如果进程在管道上进行读取，
where it knows that really nothing is waiting to be read in that pipe,
它知道在管道中没有需要等待读取的东西，
then the read will block,
那么读取就会阻塞，
you can predict the read block
你可以预测读取阻塞，
and that the kernel will run some other process,
内核将运行其他进程，
while we're waiting for data to appear in the pipe.
当我们等待数据出现在管道中时。
So the times when yield is called in the kernel,
所以，内核调用 yield 的时机，
there's really two main times,
有两个主要的时机，
one is if a timer interrupt goes off, kernel always yields,
一种是如果计时器中断，内核总会让出，
you know just on the theory that,
基于这样的理论，
we should interleave the execution of of all the process
我们应该交错执行所有这些进程，
that want to run on timer interrupt periods,
想要定期在定时器中断时运行，
so timer interrupt also always calls yield
所处，定时器中断总是调用 yield ，
and whenever a process system calls waiting for IO,
当进程系统调用等待 IO 时，
waiting for you know type the next keystroke,
等待你输入下一次按键，
does a read of the console
读取控制台，
and you haven't typed key yet,
但是你没有按键，
then the the machinery to wait for IO calls yields,
然后等待 IO 调用的机器调用 yield ，
called for sleep, something we'll talk about next week.
调用 sleep ，我们下周会谈到。
Alright.
好的。
Okay, so.
好的，那么。
I have another question.
我有一个问题。
Yes.
好的。
Oh, if it is a sleep,
如果是 sleep ，
is it gonna do the same thing roughly,
它是否会做大致相同的事，
so it's gonna be some system call,
比如会是系统调用，
there's gonna save the trapframe
保存 trapframe ，
and then basically the same [picture],
然后是一样的[图片]，
but it's just then the thing
但它只是，
that made the process go into the kernel without a timer interrupt,
使进程在没有定时器中断的情况下进入内核，
but, the process's own decision?
但是，是进程自己决定的吗？
Yeah, so the process make there's a read system call
是的，所以这个进程有一个读取系统调用，
and that's why it's in the kernel,
这就是为什么它在内核中，
and the read requires the process to wait for the disk to do to finish reading
而读取需要这个进程等待磁盘完成读取，
or to wait for data to appear on a pipe,
或者等待数据出现在管道上，
then actually the diagram is exactly the same as this,
那么图跟这个是一样的，
and the kernel with a system call,
内核中调用系统调用，
trapframe, all the saved user register,
trapframe ，所有保存的用户寄存器，
execute the system call, the system will [],
执行系统调用，系统会[]，
need to wait for the disk to finish reading something,
需要等待磁盘完成读取某些内容，
the system call code will call sleep which ends up coding switch,
系统调用调用 sleep ，包含 switch ，
which saves away the kernel thread registers in the process context
保存进程上下文中的内核线程寄存器，
switches to this current CPU scheduler,
切换到该当前 CPU 调度器，
to let some other thread run,
让其他线程运行，
while this thread is waiting for the disk read to finish.
而这个线程等待磁盘读取完成。
So everything we're going to talk about now,
所以，我们现在谈论的一切，
except for the timer interrupt,
除了定时器中断，
is pretty much the same
几乎都是一样的，
if what's going on is we're in a system called,
如果发生的情况是我们使用系统调用，
the system call needs to wait for some for IO
系统调用需要等待一些 IO ，
and give up the CPU.
并放弃 CPU 。
For the purposes of today's discussion,
对于今天的讨论，
the two situations are almost identical.
这两种情况几乎是一样的。
Okay, so the question does each per CPU scheduler has its own stack.
好的，问题是每个 CPU 调度器都有自己的堆栈吗。
Yes,
是的，
there's a stack,
这里有一个堆栈，
this scheduler stack for this separate stack,
而这个调度器有单独的堆栈，
for scheduler for CPU one.
对于 CPU1 的调度器。
Yeah, and indeed the stacks for this scheduler also setup,
是的，这个调度器的堆栈也设置好了，
in fact, all this stuff
实际上，所有这些东西，
you know the context and the stacks with a scheduler threads
上下文，堆栈，调度器线程，
are set up in a different way than for user process's.
设置与用户进程的设置方式不同。
They're set up at boot time,
它们是在引导时设置的，
if you poke around and start.S or start.c, start.S probably,
如果查看 start.S 或 start.c ，
you'll see some of the setup for each core's scheduler thread,
你会看到每个核心的调度器线程的设置，
there's a place with stack very early in the assembly code during boot,
堆栈在引导的汇编代码中非常早的位置，
where the stack is set up for each CPU
其中为每个 CPU 设置堆栈，
and it's on that stack,
在那个堆栈上，
that's a CPU boots on
CPU 引导，
and then runs its scheduler thread.
然后运行它的调度器线程。
Okay, um.
好的，嗯。
One piece of jargon,
一条行话，
when people talk about context switch,
当人们谈论上下文切换时，
they're talking about usually this act of
他们谈论的通常是这种行为，
switching from one thread to another
从一个线程切换到另一个，
by saving one set of register sets for the old thread
保存旧线程的一组寄存器，
and restoring previously saved registers for the threads were switching to,
并且恢复要切换到的线程先前保存的寄存器，
that's what's usually meant by context,
这就是上下文的意思，
which also sometimes it's applied to the complete done is
有时它也适用于完整的，
that goes on when switching from one user process to another
一个用户进程切换到另一个，
and occasionally you'll see context which apply to switching between user and kernel,
偶尔会看到在用户和内核之间切换的上下文，
but for us we mostly mean it,
但对我们来说，我们大多数的意思是，
switching from one kernel thread typically to scheduler thread.
从一个内核线程切换到调度器线程。
Just some pieces of information,
只是一些片段信息，
the [] [] to keep in mind,
要记住的[][]，
every core just does one thing at a time,
每个核心一次只做一件事，
each core you know is either is just running one thread at any given time,
每个核心在任何时间只运行一个线程，
it's either running some processes user thread some process kernel thread
它要么运行一些用户线程或一些内核线程，
or that core's scheduler thread,
或核心的调度器线程，
so at any given time the core is not doing multiple things,
所以在任何时间，核心都不会做多件事，
it's just doing one thing
它只是在做一件事，
and it's this switching that sort of creates the illusion
正是这种切换在创造了一个假象，
of multiple threads running at different times on that core,
多个线程在核心上不同时间运行，
similarly, each thread is running on,
类似地，每个线程运行在，
is either running on exactly one core
要么在一个核心上运行，
or its state has been state has been saved
或它的状态已保存，
and we switched away from it.
然后我们从它切换走。
So, so a thread,
所以，一个线程，
just to be clear, thread never runs on more than one core,
线程不会在多个核心上运行，
thread is either running on just one core
线程要么在一个核心上运行，
or it's not running at all, as a saved state somewhere.
要么根本没有运行，作为保存状态。
Another interesting thing about the xv6 setup is that
另一个关于 xv6 设置的有趣的事情是，
these contexts that hold saved kernel thread registers,
这些上下文保存内核线程寄存器，
they're always produced by a call to switch
它们总是由调用 swtch 产生，
and so these contexts basically always refer to the state of the thread
所以，这些上下文总是关联指线程的状态，
and it was executing inside a call to swtch.
它在对 swtch 的调用中执行的。
And you know the way we'll see that come up is that
我们会看到的方式是，
when we switch from one to another
当我们从一个切换到另一个，
and restore the target thread's context,
并恢复目标线程的上下文，
the first thing it will do is return from a previous call to swtch,
它要做的第一件事是从上一个调用返回到 swtch ，
these contexts are always saved state,
这些上下文总是保存状态，
in as it is in swtch.
就像它在 swtch 里一样。
Okay.
好的。
Any more questions about the diagram level situation?
关于图表级别的情况，还有什么问题吗？
I have a question,
我有一个问题，
you are using the term thread all the time,
你一直使用线程这个术语，
but it seems to me, like our implementation for xv6,
但在我看来，我们对 xv6 的实现，
a process is if there's only one thread,
一个进程只有一个线程，
so it could it be possible that one process could have multiple threads
所以，有没有可能一个进程可以有多个线程，
or am I wrong here.
还是我说错了。
In xv6, alright.
在 xv6 中，好的。
There's definitely some confusing things about the way we use the words here,
我们在这里的说法是有一些让人困惑的地方，
in xv6,
在 xv6 中，
a process,
一个进程，
a process is either executing instructions user level
一个进程执行用户级别的指令，
or it's executing instructions in the kernel
或者执行内核中的指令，
or it's not executed at all
或者根本不执行，
and its state has been saved away into this combination of context and trapframe.
它的状态被保存到上下文和 trapframe 中。
So that's the actual situation,
所以这就是实际情况，
which you want to call that,
你怎么叫它，
you call it what you like,
你想怎么叫都行，
I I don't know of a simple explanation for this structure,
我不知道对这个结构有什么简单的解释，
we've been calling it I've been calling it,
我们一直这样叫它，
I've been saying that each process has two threads,
我一直说每个进程有两个线程，
a user level thread and a kernel level thread
一个用户级线程和一个内核级线程，
and that's a process,
这是一个进程，
there's this restriction
有这样的限制，
that a process is only execute,
进程只会执行，
either executing in the kernel in the user space
或者在用户空间的内核中执行，
or executing in the kernel, inter- interrupt system call,
或者在内核中中断系统调用中，
but never both.
但不能两个同时。
That makes sense.
理解了。
Yeah, I apologize for the complexity of this.
是的，我为这件事的复杂性道歉。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, so let me switch to code,
好的，让我切换到代码，
looking at the xv6 code.
看看 xv6 代码。
Alright, so first of all,
好的，首先，
I just wanna, just show some of the stuff we've been talking about,
我展示一些我们一直在谈论的东西，
I'm going to look at the process structure.
我来看一下进程的结构。
And we can see in the process structure,
我们可以在进程结构中看到，
a lot of the things we've been talking about,
很多东西我们已经讨论过，
just for review,
复习一下，
there's the trapframe, that saves the user level registers.
这是 trapframe ，保存了用户级别寄存器。保存用户级寄存器的陷阱帧。
There's a context here, that saves the kernel thread registers,
这里有一个上下文，它保存内核线程寄存器，
which switch to the scheduler thread.
当切换到调度器线程。
There's a pointer to this process is kernel stack,
有一个指向这个进程的指针是内核堆栈，
which is where function calls are saved,
保存函数调用的位置，
while we're executing in the kernel.
当我门在内核中执行时。
There's the state variable,
这是状态变量，
which records whether this process is running or runnable
它记录该进程是否正在运行或是否可运行，
or sleeping or not allocated at all.
或者处于休眠状态或根本没有分配。
And then finally, there's a lock that protects various things as we'll see,
最后，这里有一个锁，保护我们看到的各种东西，
for now, we can observe that at least protects changes to the state variable.
目前，我们可以看到，至少保护了对状态变量的更改。
So that for example two scheduler threads,
比如，两个调度器线程，
don't try to grab a runnable process and run it at the same time.
不会试图获取一个可运行的进程并同时运行它。
One of the many things this lock does is prevent that from happening.
这个锁做的事情之一就是防止这种情况发生。
I'm gonna run a simple demo program for you, the spin program.
我要为你们运行一个简单的演示程序 spin 程序。
I'm using it mostly just to drive the
我要用它来推动，
sort of create a predictable situation
创造一种可预测的情况，
in which we switch from one thread to another,
我们从一个线程切换到另一个线程，
but this is this program,
但这就是这个程序，
spin program creates two processes
spin 程序创建了两个进程，
and the processes both compute forever,
而且这两个过程都是永远计算的，
you know call fork here,
在这里调用 fork，
I make a child
我创造了一个子程序，
and then forever, both children both children just sit in this loop
然后两个子程序永远在这个循环里，
and everyone's while print a character,
而每个进程打印一个字符，
so we can see they're making progress,
所以，我们可以看到它们的进展，
but they don't print characters very often,
但是它们不经常打印字符，
and they never sort of intentionally give up the CPU.
而且它们从来不会故意放弃 CPU 。
So what we have here is two, essentially two compute bound processes
所以我们这里有两个计算密集型进程，
and in order for both of them to run,
为了让它们两个都跑起来，
I'm gonna run them on a single CPU,
我将在单个 CPU 上运行它们，
xv6 that is only one core
只有一个核心的 xv6 ，
and so in order for both of them to execute,
所以，为了让它们两个都能执行，
you know it's going to be necessary to to switching between the two processes.
有必要在这两个进程之间切换。
Let me fire up spin program under gdb,
让我使用 gdb 把 spin 程序启动起来，
run the spin program and you can see it's printing,
运行 spin 程序，你可以看到它在打印，
one of the two processes prints forward slash
其中一个进程打印正斜杠，
and the other prints backward slash
另一个打印反斜杠，
and you can see that every once in a while,
你可以看到，每隔一段时间，
xv6 is switching between them
xv6 在它们之间切换，
and only has one core the way I've configured it,
而且只有一个核心，就像我配置的那样，
so we see a bunch of forward slashes printing
所以我们看到打印一堆正斜杠，
and then apparently a timer interrupt,
然后很明显是计时器中断，
must go off switch the one CPU to the other process
将一个 CPU 切换到另一个进程，
and then prints the other kind of slash for a while.
然后打印一会另一种斜杠。
So what I want to observe is the timer interrupt going off,
所以，我想要观察的是计时器中断的运行，
so I'm gonna put a breakpoint in trap,
所以我要在 trap 里放一个断点，
and in particular at line 207 in trap,
尤其是在 trap 中的第 207 行，
which is a code in trap in devintr,
trap 中的 devintr 代码，
that recognizes that we're in interrupt
表示我们在中断中，
and the interrupt was caused by a timer interrupt.
并且这是中断是由定时器中断引起的。
So I put a breakpoint here,
所以我在这里设置一个断点，
at trap.c 207
在 trap.c 第 207 行，
and continue [boom] the trap I triggers right away,
继续[]我刚才触发的 trap ，
because timer interrupt are pretty frequent
因为定时器中断相当频繁，
and we can tell from
我们可以从得到，
where that indeed when user trap and user trap has called devintr
用户 trap 调用 devintr 的地方，
to handle this interrupt.
来处理这个中断。
I wanna take finish to get out of devintr back into user trap.
我想离开 devintr ，回到用户 trap 中。
Because, in fact we don't,
因为，事实上我们没有，
the code devintr into timer interrupt you know says almost nothing.
devintr 到定时器中断的代码没有什么东西。
However, once we're back at in usertrap,
然而，一旦我们回到 usertrap ，
we can see that this line here,
我们可以从这一行看到，
that we just returned from devintr.
我们刚从 devintr 返回。
And the interesting thing about this is that,
有趣的是，
what we're about to do,
我们接下来要做的，
I'm looking forward we're currently at this line here
期待我们在这一行，
and we're looking forward to this call the yield,
我们期待这里调用 yield ，
when devintr return two, you can see from this,
在这里你可以看到， devintr 返回了 2 ，
the return is two,
返回的是 2 ，
two is basically the device number
2 是设备号，
and we're going to see that by and by,
我们很快就会看到这一点，
because which devices two,
因为哪个设备是 2 ，
usertrap going to call yield,
usertrap 要 yield 的，
which go to CPU and allows [pushing] the process,
它获得 CPU 并允许运行进程，
you'll see that in a moment,
你很快就会看到这一点，
meantime let's look at what was currently executing when the interrupt happened.
同时，让我们看看中断发生时正在执行的是什么。
I'm going to print p,
我要打印 p ，
the variable p holds a pointer to the current processes struct proc.
变量 p 保存着指向当前进程结构 proc 的指针。
Okay, the question what makes each processes kernel thread different.
好的，问题是什么让每个进程的内核线程不同。
Every process has a separate kernel thread,
每个进程都有单独的内核线程，
there's really two things that differentiate different processes kernel thread,
确实有两个不同的进程内核线程，
because more than one could be executing on different cores.
因为多个可以在不同的核心上执行。
One is indeed that every process has a separate kernel stack
一个是每个进程都有单独的内核堆栈，
and that's what's pointed to by that kstack element of struct proc
就是结构体 proc 的 kstack 所指向的，
and the other is that,
另一个是，
early in,
早些时候，
when usertrap which is you know the C code is called,
当 usertrap C 代码调用时，
by trampoline, when interrupt occurs.
通过 trampoline ，当中断发生时。
We can tell by this call them by any, any kernel code,
我们可以通过任何内核代码区分它们，
can tell by calling myproc what the processes is running on the current CPU.
可以通过调用 myproc 来判断当前 CPU 上正在运行哪些进程。
And that's another thing that differentiates,
这是另一个不同的地方，
that allows each, that allows kernel code to tell
这允许内核代码区分，
what process it's part of that is which processes kernel thread is executing
哪个进程内核线程正在执行，
and what myproc does basically use the tp register
而 myproc 使用的是 tp 寄存器，
which you may recall,
你可能还记得，
is set up to contain the current cores hartid or core number,
设置为包含当前核心 hartid 或核心编号，
it uses that to index into an array of structures,
使用它来索引到一个结构数组，
that say for each core that the scheduler sets
也就是说，对于调度器设置的每个核心，
whenever it switches processes to indicate for each core
每当它切换进程以指示每个核心，
which process is running on that core.
哪个进程在那个核心上运行。
And so that's how different kernels are differentiated.
这就是不同内核如何区分。
Okay, so I was going to use that p value,
好的，我要使用这个 p 的值，
the name and that p value to figure out what process is running,
名称和 p 值以确定哪个进程正在运行，
xv6 remembers the name it's that spin process just exactly as expected,
xv6 记得名字就是 spin 进程，像预期的一样，
there were two of them, I think with process ids three and four.
有两个进程，我想进程 id 分别是 3 和 4 。
Oops.
糟糕。
We're currently executed again process id three,
我们现在再次执行进程 3 ，
so after the switch we'd expect to be in process id four,
所以在切换之后，我们应该在进程 4 中，
the other spin process,
另一个 spin 进程，
and we we can look at the saved user registers in the trapframe.
我们可以查看 trapframe 中保存的用户寄存器。
And these are the 32 registers
这是 32 个寄存器，
that a trampoline code saves a way to save the user state,
trampoline 代码保存用户状态，
there's the user ra return address register user stack pointer,
用户 ra 返回用户堆栈指针的地址，
user program counter at hex 62.
用户寄存器是十六进制 62 。
These are familiar things from when we looked at traps.
这些都是我们在观察 trap 时熟悉的东西。
And you may be the most interest is that,
你可能最感兴趣的是，
the trapframe saves the user program counter and that value 62,
trapframe 保存着用户程序计数器和值 62 ，
if we cared, we can look in the assembly code for spin.c.
如果我们关心，可以查看 spin.c 的汇编代码。
Oops, spin.asm look for 62,
糟糕，在 spin.asm 查找 62 ，
now we can see that owes a interrupt timer,
我们可以看到有一个中断定时器，
interrupt occurred during this add instruction in that infinite loop in spin,
中断发生在 spin 无限循环中的加法指令期间，
so it's not too surprising.
这并不令人惊讶。
Okay, so back to a trap code [] just returned,
好的，回到刚才返回的 trap 代码，
I'm going to take step a few times to get us to the,
我要单步几次把我们带到，
just being about to execute this yield.
到达执行 yield 。
And yield is sort of the first step in the process of giving up the CPU
而 yield 是进程中让出 CPU 的第一步，
switching to the scheduler,
切换到调度器，
letting the scheduler choose another kernel thread in process to run.
让调度器选择进程中的另一个内核线程来运行。
Alright, so let's actually step into yield,
好的，让我们单步进入 yield ，
now we're in yield, yield's.
现在我们在 yield ， yield 是。
If you have a question.
你有什么问题吗。
No.
不是。
Okay, we're in yield,
好的，我们在 yield 中，
yield does a couple of things,
yield 做了几件事，
it acquires the lock for this process,
它获取这个进程的锁，
because it's about to make a bunch of changes to this process,
因为它要对这个进程进行一系列的修改，
and it doesn't want any other
而且它不希望有任何其他的，
and in fact until it gives up the lock,
实际上，在它放弃锁之前，
the state of this process will be sort of in consistent
这个进程的状态会是一致的，
like for example, it's about yield is about to change the state of the process to runnable,
比如， yield 将进程的状态更改为可运行，
which would you know indicates that,
这表明，
the process is not running, but would like to,
这个进程没有在运行，但希望运行，
but this process is running, right,
但是这个进程是在运行的，
I mean we're running the process right now,
我是说，我们正在运行这个进程，
that's what's executing is the kernel thread for this process
就是正在执行的这个进程的内核线程，
and so the one of the many things that acquire this lock does is,
所以，获取这个锁所做的事情之一是，
makes it, so that even though we just changed the state runnable,
让它，尽管我们修改状态为可运行，
no other core's scheduling thread will look at this process
没有其他核心的调度线程会看到这个进程，
and because of lock
因为使用了锁，
and see that it's runnable and try to run it
（其他核心）看到它是可运行的，并试着运行它，
while we're still running it on this core,
当我们还在这个核心上运行它时，
would be a disaster right,
将会是一场灾难，
running the same process on two different cores,
在两个不同的核心上运行相同的进程，
you know process has only one stack,
你知道进程只有一个堆栈，
so that means like two different cores are calling [subroutines] on the same stack,
这意味着两个不同的核心在同一个堆栈上调用[子例程]，
which is just a [recipe] for disaster.
这是一个灾难。
So we take the lock out,
所以，我们使用了锁，
we, yield changes the state to runnable.
yield 把状态改为可运行。
And what this mean is that,
这意味着，
you know we finally given up the,
我们最终放弃了，
when we finally yield the CPU and given it up
当我们最终放弃 CPU ，
and switch the scheduler process,
切换到调度器进程，
this state will be left in this runnable state,
这个状态会保持在可运行状态，
so that it will run again,
这样它就可以再次运行，
because after all this was a timer interrupt,
毕竟这是一个计时器中断，
that interrupted a running user level process,
中断了正在运行的用户级进程，
that would like to continue computing.
它希望继续运行。
We're gonna leave state runnable,
我们把状态设置为可运行，
so that it will run again,
让它可以再次运行，
as soon as the scheduler decides to.
一旦调度器做了决定。
And then, the only other thing that,
然后，另一件事情是，
yield does is call this scheduler function.
yield 调用了这个调度器函数。
So I'm going to step into the scheduler function.
所以，我要单步执行调度器函数。
I'll show this whole thing here.
我会在这里展示整个过程。
This scheduler is something does almost nothing,
这个调度器几乎什么都不做，
it does a bunch of checks,
它做了一些检查，
it does a whole bunch of sanity checks and panics
它做了一些可用性检查和 panic ，
and the reason for that is actually that,
这个原因是，
this code in xv6,
xv6 中的这段代码，
over its many year lifetime had been among the most bug [prone]
在多年的时间中，一直是最容易出错的，
and have most surprises unhappy surprises,
有最多的意外，不愉快的意外，
so there's a lot of sanity checks and panics here,
所以这里有很多可用性检查和 panic ，
because, because there's often bugs associated with this code.
因为经常会有与这些代码相关的 bug 。
Alright, I'm gonna skip over these sanity checks
好的，我会跳过这些可用性检查，
and proceed to the call to swtch,
然后继续到调用 swtch ，
this call to switch is where the real action happens,
这个调用 swtch 是真正的操作发生的地方，
this is call the switch
这个调用 swtch ，
is going to save away the current kernel threads registers in p->context,
将保存目前的内核线程寄存器到 p-> context 中，
which is the current process's saved kernel thread context, save set of registers,
是当前进程保存内核线程上下文，保存寄存器，
c->context, c is the pointer to this core's struct cpu,
c->context ， c 是指向核心 CPU 结构的指针，
struct cpu has context to save registers of this core's scheduler threads,
CPU 结构体具有保存这个核心调度器线程的寄存器的上下文，
we're going to be switching from this thread
我们将从这个线程切换，
and saving this thread state,
保存这个线程的状态，
restoring the thread state of this core's scheduler
恢复核心调度器的线程状态，
and continuing the execution of this core's core's scheduler thread.
并继续运行这个核心的调度器线程。
Okay, so let's see what,
好的，让我们看看是，
let's take a quick preview at the context
让我们快速看一下上下文，
that we're going to be switching to
我们将切换到的，
and I can get that turns out that,
我可以得出，
I can't actually print c->context,
我不能直接打印 c->context ，
but I happen to know that c prints to cpus zero,
但我知道 c 打印 cpus[0] ，
just because we're on the zero with core,
因为我们在核心 0 上，
there's only one core,
只有一个核心，
and I can print its context.
我可以打印它的上下文。
And so this is the saved registers from this core's, scheduler thread.
这就是这个核心的调度器线程中保存的寄存器。
And of particular interest is the ra,
特别感兴趣的是 ra ，
because the ra register is where the current function call is going to return to,
因为 ra 寄存器是当前函数调用要返回的地方，当前函数调用将返回到，
so we're going to switch the scheduler thread,
所以我们要切换调度器线程，
it's going to do return and return to that ra.
它会返回，并返回到 ra 。
And we can find out
我们可以找到，
where that where that return address by looking in kernel.asm.
通过查看 kernel.asm ，找到那个返回地址。
Actually that's.
实际上，那是。
And as you can see this x/i,
你可以看到的，这个 x/i ，
you know prints instructions that at a certain address,
打印某个地址的指令，
but it also prints the label of the name of the function
但它也会打印函数的名称标签，
that those instructions are in it,
那些指令在这个函数里面，
so we're going to be returning to scheduler by and by,
所以我们很快会回到调度器上，
that's just you know as you might expect.
这正是你希望的。
Okay.
好的。
I want to look at what swtch actually does,
我想看看 swtch 做了什么，
about to call swtch.
关于调用 swtch 。
So I put a breakpoint on swtch
所以我在 swtch 上设置一个断点，
and putting a breakpoint,
设置断点，
because there's a bunch of setup code
因为这里有一堆设置代码，
that pulls the values of context out of those structures,
将上下文的值从这些结构中提取出来，
I'll skip over it.
我会跳过它。
Okay, so now,
好的，现在，
when a breakpoint at swtch,
当到达 swtch 断点时，
the gdb won't show us the instructions,
GDB 不会给我们看指令，
but we can look at switch.S
但是我们可以查看 switch.S ，
to look at the instructions we're about to execute.
来查看即将执行的指令。
So as you can see we're on the very first instruction,
正如你看到的，我们在第一条指令，
the store of ra to the address pointed to by a0,
将 ra 保存到 a0 指向的地址，
you may remember in the call to swtch,
你可能还记得在调用 swtch 中，
that the first argument was the current thread's context
第一个参数是当前线程的上下文，
and the second argument was the context of the thread we're switching to,
第二个参数是我们要切换到的线程的上下文，
the two arguments going a0 and a1.
两个参数分别到 a0 和 a1 。
And so the reason why we see all these stores through register a0 is
所有保存都要通过寄存器 a0 的原因是，
because we're storing away a bunch of registers in the memory that a0 points to
是因为我们在 a0 指向的内存中保存了一堆寄存器，
that is in the context of the thread we're switching from
是我们切换的线程的上下文，
and the loads load from address a1,
而加载从地址 a1 中加载，
because that's a pointer to the context of the thread, we're switching to.
因为这是指向我们要切换到的线程的上下文的指针。
Okay, and so thread, you know, swtch saves registers, loads registers
好的，线程， swtch 保存寄存器，加载寄存器，
from the target thread's context and then return
从目标线程的上下文中，然后返回，
and that's why the ra was interesting,
这就是为什么 ra 很有趣，
because it's going to return to the place that ra pointed to namely into scheduler.
因为它返回 ra 指向的位置，即进入调度器。
Alright, so one question is you may notice here
好的，这里有一个问题，你可能会注意到，
that while swtch saves ra sp and a bunch of s registers,
虽然 swtch 保存了 ra sp 和很多 s 寄存器，
one that does not save is the program counter,
却没有保存程序计数器，
there's no mention of the program counter here,
这里没有提到程序计数器，
so why is that.
那是为什么。
Is it because the program counter is updated with like the function calls anyway.
是不是因为程序计数器在函数任何时候调用时都是更新的。
Yeah it's it's the program counter, there's no actual information value in the program counter,
是的，程序计数器里没有实际的信息值，
we know that we're executing right now is in switch, right.
我们知道正在执行的是 swtch 。
So there be no point in saving the program counter,
因此没有保存程序计数器，
because it has an extremely predictable value namely this instruction,
因为它有一个可预测的值，也就是这条指令，
the address of this instruction of swtch
swtch 指令的地址，
what we really care about is where we we're called from,
我们真正关心的是我们从哪里被调用，
because when we switch back to this thread,
因为当我们切换回这个线程时，
we want to continue executing out whatever points swhich was called from
我们希望继续从调用点执行，
and it's ra,
它就是 ra ，
that holds the address of the instruction that swtch was called from.
保存着调用 swtch 指令的地址。
So it's ra, that's being saved away here,
所以是 ra 被保存在这里，
and ra is the point at which will be executing out again.
而 ra 是再次执行的点。
Let's swtch return,
让 swtch 返回，
so we even print that we can print,
我们甚至可以打印，
ra, oops.
ra ，糟糕。
We can print ra
我们可以打印 ra ，
and you know we haven't actually switched threads yet,
我们还没有切换线程，
you remember we came here from this sched function,
还记得我们是从这个 sched 函数过来的，
so ra as you might expect the pointer back into this sched function.
所以，如你所想的， ra 指向 sched 函数。
Another question is,
另一个问题是，
how come swtch only saves 14 registers,
为什么 swtch 只保存了 14 个寄存器，
I counted them,
我数了一下，
it only saves and restores 14 registers,
它只保存和恢复 14 个寄存器，
even though the RISC-V has 32 registers
尽管 RISC-V 有 32 个寄存器，
available for the or use it for code to use.
可用于，代码可以使用。
Why, why only half the registers are saved?
为什么只保存了一半的寄存器？
Well, when swtch was called, it was called as a normal function,
当调用 swtch 时，它是作为正常函数调用的，
so whoever called swtch already assumed will swtch might modify those,
所以，任何调用 swtch 都会假设 swtch 可能会修改这些，
so that that function already saved that on its stack,
以便那个函数将其保存在它的堆栈中，
meaning that like when we jump from one to the other,
这意味着当我们从一个跳到另一个的时候，
that one is gonna self restore its caller-saved registers.
它会自动恢复调用者保存寄存器。
That's exactly right,
完全正确，
the swtch are called from C code,
这个 swtch 是由 C 代码调用的，
we know that the C compiler saves on the current stack,
我们知道 C 编译器保存在当前堆栈上，
any caller saved registers,
任何调用者保存寄存器，
that have values in them that the compiler's going to need later.
包含编译器之后需要的值。
And those caller saved registers actually include,
而那些调用者保存寄存器包括，
I think there's 18,
我想有 18 个，
depending on how you count them,
取决于你如何计算它们，
there's somewhere between fifteen and eighteen caller saved registers,
有 15 到 18 个调用者保存寄存器，
so the registers we see here are all the registers that aren't caller saved
所以，我们在这里看到的寄存器是所有不是调用者保存的寄存器，
and that the compiler doesn't promise to save,
编译器没有保证保存，
but nevertheless may hold values that are needed by the calling function,
但是仍然可以保存调用函数所需的值，
so we all need to save the callee saved registers, when we're switching threads.
所以当我们切换线程时，只需要保存被调用者保存的寄存器。
Okay.
好的。
Final thing I want to print is the,
我想打印的最后一个东西是，
we do save and restore the stack pointer,
我们保存和恢复了堆栈指针，
the current stack pointer, it's like hard to tell from this value,
当前堆栈指针，很难从这个值判断，
what that means, that it's the kernel stack of the current process,
这意味着，它是当前进程的内核堆栈，
which I don't know if you recall,
我不知道你是否记得，
but is allocated is mapped by the virtual memory system at high memory.
但是是由虚拟内存系统在高内存映射的。
Okay, so, okay, so we're going to save away the current registers
好的，我们要保存当前的寄存器，
and restore registers from scheduler thread's context,
从调度器线程的上下文中恢复寄存器，
I don't want to execute every single one of these load or store,
我不想执行每一个加载或保存，
so I'm gonna step over,
所以我要跳过，
all the 14 loads, the 14 stores and the 14 loads,
所有这 14 个保存和 14 个加载，
going to proceed directly to the return instructions.
直接到返回指令。
Okay, so we executed everything in swtch, except the return,
好的，所以我们执行了 swtch 中的所有代码，除了返回，
before we do the return,
在我们返回之前，
we'll just print the interesting registers again,
我们再次打印感兴趣的寄存器，
to see where we are.
看看我们在哪里。
So stack pointer, now it has a different value,
所以堆栈指针，现在它有一个不同的值，
stack pointer now points into this stack zero area in memory,
堆栈指针现在指向内存中的堆栈零区域，
and this is actually the place it very very early in the boot sequence
这是在引导序列中非常早的位置，
where start.S puts the stack,
在 start.S 中放置堆栈，
so it may call the very first C function,
以便它可以调用第一个 C 函数，
so actually back on the original boot stack for this CPU
所以回到这个 CPU 的初始引导堆栈，
which just happens to be where the scheduler runs.
它恰好就是调度器运行的地方。
Okay, the program counter actually interesting,
好的，我们对程序计数器也很感兴趣，
we're in swtch because we haven't returned yet
我们在 swtch 中，因为我们还没有返回，
and the ra register now points the scheduler,
并且现在 ra 寄存器指向调度器，
because we've loaded,
因为我们已经加载，
we've restored the register set previously saved by the scheduler thread.
我们已经恢复了之前由调度器线程保存的寄存器集。
And indeed, we're really now in the scheduler thread,
实际上，我们现在在调度器线程中，
if I run on where,
如果我执行 where ，
the where now looks totally different from the last time we ran,
返回结果跟上次执行完全不一样了，
it were now indeed a call to swtch,
它现在是调用 swtch ，
but now we're in a call from swtch
但是现在我们调用 swtch ，
to switch the scheduler may at some point in the past
要切换到过去某个时间调度器，
and the scheduler was run long ago during boot
调度器很久以前就在引导期间运行了，
was called as the last thing that [] did during the boot process.
是在引导过程中所调用的最后一件事。
So I'm gonna ask you know one instruction to return from switch now into scheduler.
所以，我要执行一条指令，从 swtch 返回到调度器。
So now we're in this core's scheduler,
现在我们在这个内核的调度器中，
look the full code,
看看完整的代码，
so this is the scheduler code,
这是调度器代码，
this function called scheduler,
这个函数叫做 scheduler ，
now we're executing in the scheduler thread for the CPU,
现在我们在 CPU 调度器线程中执行，
and we're just at the point,
我们在，
we just returned from a previous call to swtch
我们从之前的调用返回到 swtch ，
the scheduler made a while ago,
它是调度器在之前创建的，
when it decided it was going to start running that process,
当它决定开始运行这一进程时，
you know pid 3 which was the spin process that was interrupted,
pid 3 ，它是被中断的 spin 进程，
so now it's this swtch process id 3,
所以现在这个 swtch 进程 id 是 3 ，
that's spin called swtch,
是 spin 调用的 swtch ，
but it's not swtch that swtch this returning
但这次返回的不是之前的 swtch ，
last swtch hasn't returned yet
之前的 swtch 还没有返回，
is still saved away in process id three stack and context
仍保存在进程 id 3 堆栈和上下文中，
just return from this earlier called swtch.
只是从先前的 swtch 返回。
Alright, so the stuff that happens here in the scheduler,
好的，在调度器中发生的事情，
were stopped running this process
已停止运行这个进程，
and so you want to forget about the various things we did,
所以你可以忘掉我们所做的各种事情，
in the process of running this process,
在运行这个进程的过程中，
we want to [forget] the c->proc equals zero,
我们希望[忽略] c->proc 等于零，
basically means that we're forgetting that.
意味着我们忘了这个。
We're no longer running this process in this core's,
我们不再在这个核心中运行这个进程，
so we don't want to have anybody be confused about that,
所以我们不想让任何人对此感到困惑，
let me set this per core proc pointer to zero [] this process,
让我把每个核心进程指针设置为零，
the next thing that happens is that,
接下来发生的事情是，
you remember yield, acquired the lock for this process,
你记得 yield ，获取这个进程的锁，
because it didn't want any other core's scheduler
因为它不想任何其他核心调度器
to look at this process and maybe run it
看到这个进程并可能运行它，
until the process was completely put to sleep.
直到这个进程完全进入休眠状态。
We've now completed the switch away from this process,
我们现在已经完成了从这个进程的切换，
so we can release the lock on the process that just yield,
这样我们可以释放对刚刚让出的进程的锁，
that's the release,
这就是 release ，
at this point, we're still in the scheduler,
在这一点上，我们还在调度器中，
if there was another core,
如果还有另一个核心，
at this point, some other core's scheduler could find that process,
在这时，其他核心调度器可以找到这个进程，
because it's runnable and run it.
因为它是可运行的，并运行它。
But that's okay,
不过，没关系，
because we've completely saved its registers,
因为我们已经完全保存了它的寄存器，
we're no longer executing on its that processes stack,
不再在那个进程堆栈上执行，
because now executing on the this core's scheduler stack,
因为现在在这个核心的调度器堆栈上执行，
so it's actually fine if some other core decides to run that process.
所以，如果其他核心决定运行这个进程，也没什么问题。
Okay, but there's no other core,
好的，但是这里没有其他核心，
so that doesn't actually happen in this demonstration.
所以在这个演示中并没有发生。
Actually, I want to spend a moment talking about the p->lock a little bit more,
实际上，我想花点时间再谈一下 p->lock ，
p->lock actually does a couple of things,
p->lock 做了几件事，
it does really two things from the point of view of scheduling,
从调度器的角度来看，它做了两件事，
one is that yielding the CPU,
一个是让出 CPU ，
involves multiple steps,
涉及多个步骤，
we have to set the state to runnable,
我们必须设置状态为可运行的，
change the state from running to runnable,
将状态从运行中改为可运行，
we save the registers in the yielding processes context,
我们将寄存器保存在让出进程的上下文中，
now we have to stop using the yielding processes stack,
现在我们必须停止使用让出进程的堆栈，
there's at least three steps,
至少有三个步骤，
which take time in order to do all the steps required to yield the CPU
需要时间来做这些步骤让出 CPU ，
and so one of the things that lock does
所以锁做的一件事是，
as I mentioned is
正如我提到的，
prevent any other core scheduler from looking at our process
阻止任何其他核心调度器看到我们的进程，
until all three steps have completed,
直到所有三个步骤完成之前，
so the lock is basically making those steps atomic,
所以锁是把这些步骤变成原子性的，
they either all happened from the point of view of other cores,
从其他核心的角度来看，它们都发生，
or none of them happened.
或者它们都不发生。
It's going to turn out also when we start running a process
当我们开始运行一个进程时，
that the p->lock is going to have a similar protective function,
p->lock 也具有类似的保护功能，
we're going to set the state of a process to running,
我们将进程的状态设置为运行中，
when we start executing a process
当我们开始执行进程时，
and we're going to move its registers from its process context into the RISC-V registers,
我们把它的寄存器从它的进程上下文转移到 RISC-V 寄存器中，
but, if an interrupt should happen in the middle of that process,
但是，如果在进程中间发生中断，
the interrupt going to see the process in a weird state
中断会看到进程处于一种奇怪的状态，
like maybe in the state of mark running,
比如状态标记为运行中，
but hasn't yet finished moving its registers from the context into the RISC-V registers,
但是没有完成将寄存器从上下文移动到 RISC-V 寄存器，
and that would be a disaster,
那将是一场灾难，
if a timer interrupt happened in,
如果发生定时器中断，
because we might switch away from that process,
因为我们可能会离开这个过程，
before it had restored its registers.
在它恢复寄存器之前。
And switching away from that process
从这个进程中离开，
would save now uninitialized RISC-V registers into the context process's context,
会保存未初始化的 RISC-V 寄存器到进程的上下文，
overwriting its real registers.
覆盖它的真正的寄存器。
So indeed we want starting a process that also be effectively atomic,
所以，实际上，我们也希望启动一个进程具有原子性，
and in this case holding a lock,
在这种情况下，持有一个锁，
holding p->lock across switching to a process
在切换到进程的过程中持有 p->lock ，
as well as preventing other cores from looking at that process
为了防止其他核心看到这个进程，
also turns off interrupts for the duration of [firing] up of switching to that thread
还会在切换到那个线程的[]持续时间内关闭中断，
which prevents a timer interrupt from ever seeing
防止定时器中断看到，
a process that's only midway through being switched to.
只切换到一半的进程。
Okay.
好的。
So we're in the scheduler,
所以我们在调度器中，
we're executing this loop in the scheduler's,
我们在调度器的循环中执行，
loop in the scheduler's that looks at all the process
调度器中的循环，依次查看所有进程，
in turn to find one to run
以找到一个要运行的进程，
and in this case, we know there's another process,
在这种情况下，我们知道还有另一个进程，
because, there's that other spin process that we've forked,
因为，还有另一个我们 fork 的 spin 进程，
but there's a lot of process lots to examine,
但是有很多东西要检查，
I'm going to skip over the actual process scanning of the process table
我将跳过扫描进程表，
and go direct to the point of which, the scheduler finds the next process,
直接调到到调度器找到下一个进程的点，
so I'm gonna put a breakpoint at line 474,
所以我要把断点放在第 474 行，
where it's actually found a new process to run.
在那里它找到了一个要运行的新进程。
[] here we are, the schedulers scan the process table
[]在这里，调度器扫描进程表，
and found another process to run.
并找到另一个要运行的进程。
And it's going to call that process run,
它会调用那个进程运行，
you can see a line 468,
你可以看第 468 行，
it acquired that process's lock,
它获取了那个进程锁，
so now it's entitled to do the various steps
所以现在它有权做不同的步骤，
were required to switch to that process,
切换到那个进程，
in line 473, it set the process of state to running,
在第 473 行，它将进程状态设置为运行中，
it's now at 474,
现在是第 474 行，
we're going to record in the CPU structure which process the CPU is executing
我们在 CPU 结构中记录 CPU 正在执行的进程，
and then call swtch to save the scheduler's registers
然后调用 swtch 来保存调度器的寄存器，
and restore the target processor's registers,
并恢复目标处理器的寄存器，
so you can see what process is found
你可以看到找到了什么进程，
by looking at the new process name,
通过查看新的进程名称，
surprisingly its spin,
当然它是 spin ，
it's process id is now four,
它的进程 id 现在是 4 ，
used to be running three now running four.
以前是 3 ，现在是 4 。
We've already set the state to running,
我们已经将状态设置为运行中，
so just the states running.
所以状态是运行中。
We can see where this thread is going to switch to
我们可以看到这个线程将切换到哪里，
in the call to swtch line 475,
在调用 swtch 的第 475 行，
print this context the saved registers,
打印上下文保存的寄存器，
so where is the ra,
那么 ra 在哪里，
we're going to call swtch,
我们要调用 swtch ，
but switch as we know it returns,
但是正如我们知道的， swtch 返回，
when it returns it returns to the restore ra,
当它返回时，返回到恢复的 ra ，
so we really care about is where is it that ra points to,
所以我们关心的是 ra 指向哪里，
we can find that out by.
我们可以通过以下方式找出。
Oops.
糟糕。
Using x/i,
使用 x/i ，
it's going to return ra points to some point instead,
它返回 ra 指向某个点，
that's not too surprising,
这并不令人惊讶，
presumably that other spin process was suspended due to a timer interrupt,
假设另一个 spin 进程由于定时器中断而挂起，
which as we know called sched, what's called swtch.
我们知道调用 sched ，调用 swtch 。
Alright, so about to call swtch,
好了，现在要调用 swtch 了，
let me just bring up the swtch code again.
让我再次打开 swtch 代码。
Actually enter swtch were still,
实际上在 swtch 中仍然，
where shows that were still in the scheduler's context.
仍然在调度器上下文中。
I want to again execute all of the instructions of swtch,
我要再次执行所有 swtch 的指令，
this time switching from the scheduler to the new process.
这次，从调度器切换到新进程。
We skip over the 28 stores and loads.
我们跳过 28 个加载和保存。
Just convince ourselves that we are actually about to return to sched,
说服我们，要回到 sched 了，
so now since we're about to return to sched and not scheduler,
既然我们要返回 sched 而不是 scheduler ，
we must now be in a process's kernel thread
我们现在必须在进程的内核线程中，
and no longer the scheduler of thread,
而不再是调度器线程，
indeed if we look at the backtrace,
事实上，如果我们查看 backtrace ，
we had a usertrap call,
我们有一个 usertrap 调用，
that must have been a timer interrupt,
这一定是定时器中断，
from long you know sometime in the past,
在过去的某个时候，
that as we've seen called yield and sched,
正如我们所看到的，调用 yield 和 sched ，
but it was the timer interrupted the other process now,
但它是定时器中断另一个进程，
not in the process that we originally looked at.
不是在我们最初观察的进程中。
Okay, any questions about,
好的，有什么问题吗，
I think I'm gonna leave off stepping through the code at this point,
我要停止一步步介绍代码了，
any questions about any of the material we've seen.
关于我们看过的任何材料，有什么问题吗。
Oh, sorry if it was, for example this [],
不好意思，如果它是这样，比如这个[]，
then we would see that ra would point somewhere to
然后我们会看到 ra 会指向某个地方
like sleep or something like that, right.
比如睡眠之类的，是吗？
Um, yes.
嗯，是的。
Well, we see that the where at this point
好的，我们在这里看到的 where ，
would include some system call implementation functions
会包含一些系统调用实现函数，
and a call to sleep,
并且调用 sleep ，
as it happens I think this is,
我想这是，
you're basically answering questions, yes,
简单回答你的问题，是的，
if we had just left off executing this process
如果我们停止执行这个进程，
for some reason other than the timer interrupt,
因为不是定时器中断的原因，
swtch would be basically returning to some system call code instead of to sched,
swtch 将返回到某些系统调用代码，而不是 sched ，
as it happens I think sleep may call sched, so.
我认为 sleep 可能调用 sched ，所以。
The backtrace would look different,
backtrace 看起来会不一样，
what just happened include sched, I guess,
我想会包含 sched ，
I've chosen just one way of,
我只选择了一种方式，
you know just one way of switching between processes due to timer interrupts.
因为定时器中断而产生的进程切换。
But you also get switches to wait for user IO,
但是你也可以切换等待用户 IO ，
wait for other processes to do things like write to pipe.
等待其他进程执行比如写入管道的操作。
Okay, one thing to you probably noticed is that
好的，有一件事你可能会注意到，
scheduler call swtch,
调度器调用 swtch ，
and what about to return from swtch here,
这里 swtch 返回的是什么，
but we're returning really from a different call to swtch
但是我们是从一个不同的调用 swtch 返回，
than them on the scheduler are made,
而不是调度器创建的，
we're returning from a call to swtch that this process made a long time ago.
我们是从这个进程很久以前调用 swtch 返回的。
So, you know, this is potentially a little bit confusing,
所以，这可能有点令人困惑，
but, you know, this is how the [] of a thread switch work.
但是，这就是线程切换[]的工作原理。
Another thing to notice is that,
另一个需要注意的事情是，
the code we're looking at,
我们正在查看的代码，
this swtch code, this is really the heart of thread switching.
这个 swtch 代码，是线程切换的核心。
And really all you have to do to switch switch threads is
你要切换线程所做的就是，
save registers and restore registers,
保存寄存器和恢复寄存器，
threads have a lot more state than just registers,
线程有比寄存器多的状态，
they have variables and stuff in the heap
它们在堆里有变量和东西，
and who knows what,
无论什么，
all that other state is in-memory
所有其他状态都在内存中，
and isn't going to be disturbed,
不会受到干扰，
we've done nothing to disturb any of these threads stacks,
我们没有做任何事情来干扰这些线程堆栈，
for example or heap values,
比如堆里的值，
so the registers in the microprocessor are really the only kind of volatile state,
所以微处理器的寄存器实际上是唯一一种易失性状态，
that actually needs to be saved and restored to do a thread switch,
需要保存和恢复才能进行线程切换，
all the stuffs in memory stack, for example,
内存堆栈中的所有内容，
will still be in memory on undisturbed
仍会在内存中原封不动，
and so it doesn't have to be explicitly saved and restored.
所以，它不需要显式地保存和恢复。
Now we're only saving and restoring this microprocessor, the CPU registers,
我们只保存和恢复微处理器 CPU 寄存器，
because we want to reuse those [] registers in the CPU for the new thread
因为我们想为新线程重新使用这些寄存器，
and overwrite whatever values they have.
覆盖它们包含的任何值。
So, register, that's why we have to save the old thread's registers.
所以，这就是为什么我们必须保存旧线程的寄存器。
What about, other processors state,
那么，其他处理器的状态呢，
so I don't know the RISC-V processor that we're using has other flags,
我不知道我们使用的 RISC-V 处理器有没有其他标志，
but I know like some x86 Intel chips have like like the floating point unit state
但我知道有些 x86 英特尔芯片有浮点单元状态
and like things like that,
或类似的东西，
do we do we just not have that in RISC-V?
在 RISC-V 中有没有这个？
Your point's very well taken on other microprocessors like x86,
你的观点在其他微处理器如 x86 上得到了很好的[理解]，
the details switching are a bit different,
切换的细节略有不同，
because they have different registers in different state
因为它们在不同的状态有不同的寄存器，
and so the code this is very very RISC-V dependent code
所以这是非常依赖于 RISC-V 的代码，
and the switch routine for some other processor might look quite different,
对于其他处理器，切换程序可能看起来不同，
like indeed might have to save floating point registers,
比如可能必须保存浮点寄存器，
you know RISC-V actually uses the general purpose registers.
RISC-V 使用的是通用寄存器。
Actually, I'm not sure what it does for floating point,
实际上，我不确定它对浮点数有什么作用，
but the kernel doesn't use floating point,
但是内核不使用浮点，
so you don't have to worry about it,
所以不用担心它，
but yeah this is totally microprocessor dependent.
但是，是的，这完全依赖于微处理器。
A question about the timer interrupts.
一个关于定时器中断的问题。
So it sounds like the the core of all of this scheduling working is that
所以听起来像是所有调度工作的核心是，
there will be a timer interrupt,
有一个定时器中断，
what happens in cases where that malfunctions.
如果它出现故障会发生什么？
There is going to be a timer interrupt.
这里会有一个定时器中断。
So the, I know so,
所以，我知道，
okay, so the reasoning for how come preemptive scheduling of user process's works is
好的，用户进程的抢占式调度能起作用的原因是，
that user processes execute with interrupts turned on always,
用户进程总是在打开中断的情况下执行，
xv6 just ensures that interrupts are enabled before returning to user space
xv6 确保在返回用户空间之前启用中断，
and that means that a timer interrupt can happen if you're executing in user space,
这意味着如果在用户空间中执行，可以发生定时器中断，
so there's nothing a user process,
所以用户进程不可能，
if on user space that timer interrupt just will happen,
如果在用户空间，定时器中断就会发生，
when the time comes.
当时间到来的时候。
So a little trickier in the kernel,
所以，在内核中有一点微妙之处，
the kernel sometimes turns off interrupts,
内核有时会关闭中断，
like when you acquire a lock,
比如，当你获取锁的时候，
the interrupts are going to be turned off,
中断将被关闭，
until you release it.
直到你释放它。
So.
所以。
So if there were some bugs in the kernel,
所以，如果内核中有一些 bug ，
if the kernel turned off interrupts
如果内核关闭中断，
and never turn them back on
没有再打开它们，
and the code in the kernel never gave up the CPU
内核中的代码不会放弃 CPU ，
never called sleep,
从来没有调用 sleep ，
gave up the CPU for any other reason,
或者因为任何其他原因放弃 CPU ，
then indeed timer interrupt would occur
那么会发生计时器中断，
and that would mean that,
这意味着，
this kernel code, may you know, would never give the CPU,
这个内核代码，可能永远不会放弃 CPU ，
but in fact, as far as we know xv6 [] xv6,
但是，据我们所知， xv6 []，
so that it always turns interrupts back on,
所以它总是重新打开中断，
or you know, if there's code in xv6, it turns off interrupts,
或者，如果在 xv6 中有关闭中断的代码，
it has to turns them back on
它必须重新打开中断，
and so timer interrupt can then occur in the kernel,
所以定时器中断可以在内核中发生，
and we can switch away from this kernel thread
我们可以从这个内核线程切换，
or the code returns back to user space,
或者代码返回到用户空间，
kernel code turns back to user space,
内核代码返回到用户空间，
we believe there's never a situation
我们相信不会出现这种情况，
in which kernel code will simply like loop with interrupts turned off forever.
内核代码在中断关闭的情况下永远循环。
I got, my question was more about like,
我知道了，我的问题更多的是关于，
so I assume the interrupts are actually coming from some piece of hardware,
所以我假设中断来自某个硬件，
what if that piece of hardware malfunctions.
如果那个硬件出现故障。
No.
不。
It's all right, then your computer is broken, you should buy a new one.
没关系，那是你的电脑坏了，你应该买一台新的。
Okay.
好的。
I mean that's a valid question for,
我是说，这是一个合理的问题，
there's you know 10 billion transistors in your computer,
你的计算机里有 100 亿个晶体管，
and indeed sometimes the hardware just like has bugs in it,
的确，有时硬件会有 bug ，
but that's beyond our reach for.
但这超出了我们的范围。
I mean, if you add 1 and 1 and the computer says 3,
我是说，如果你计算 1+1 ，而电脑给出 3，
then you just have deep problems,
那么你遇到深层次的问题，
that xv6 can't help you with.
xv6 不能帮你解决。
So we're assuming that the computer works.
所以，我们假设计算机是可以工作的。
The only time when that when software,
唯一一次，软件可以，
I mean, there are times when software tries to compensate for hardware level errors,
我是说，有时软件会试图弥补硬件错误，
like if you're sending packets across the network,
比如，如果你通过网络发送数据包，
you always send a checksum,
总是发送校验和，
so that if the network hardware flips a bit,
如果网络硬件翻转了一个位，
malfunctions flips a bit,
出现故障翻转了一个位，
then you can correct that,
那么你可以纠正这个，
but for stuff inside the computer,
但是对于计算机里的东西，
people tend not to,
人们往往不会，
it's just,
它只是，
people basically don't try to make the software compensate for hardware errors.
人们不会试图让软件来弥补硬件错误。
Oh, I have a question,
我有个问题，
why so like in trampoline dot, actually in swtch,
为什么在 trampoline. ，在 swtch 中，
we write the code in assembly,
我们用汇编语言编写代码，
is that why,
这是因为，
is that because we want to make sure that exactly this thing happen,
是不是因为我们要确保这件事的发生，
so we cannot, you cann't write in C,
所以我们不能用 C 写，
because we just need,
因为我们需要，
it feels like those exact things to happen basically.
[感觉]这些事情发生。
Yeah yeah.
是的，是的。
Yes, certainly we want this exact sequence to happen,
是的，我们当然希望这个确切的顺序发生，
and C it it's very hard to talk about things like ra in C or sp
C 很难访问像 ra 或 sp 这样的东西，
certainly there's no way within the C language
当然，在 C 语言中，也没有办法
to talk about changing the stack pointer with ra register,
使用 ra 寄存器访问修改堆栈指针，
so these are things that, just can't be you can't see it in ordinary C,
这些东西不能在普通的 C 中看到，
the only way you can see it in C is
你能在 C 中看到它的唯一方式是，
there, there is possible in C to sort of embed assembly instructions in C code,
在 C 代码中嵌入汇编语言指令，
so we could have just embedded these assembly instructions in the C function,
所以我们可以把这些汇编指令嵌入到 C 函数中，
but, would amount to the same thing.
但是，这就等同于一件事了。
We're basically we're operating at a level below below C,
我们是在低于 C 的级别下操作的，
so we can't really can't really use C here.
所以我们不能在这里使用 C 。
I have a question,
我有个问题，
about when a thread finishes executing
关于当线程完成执行，
and assuming that happens in the user space
假设发生在用户空间，
when we call the exec, I'm sorry, [exec] system call
当我们调用 exec 系统调用，
and that also ends the process,
它也结束了进程，
the thread assuming in the kernel space,
在内核空间的线程，
but if the thread ends within before a new timer interrupt happens,
但是如果线程在新的定时器中断发生之前结束，
does it still look like,
它是否还是，
is this like the CPU still acquire by that thread
比如 CPU 还在被那个线程获取，
or do we end that thread and start a new one
或者结束那个线程并开始一个新的，
before the new timer interrupt.
在新的定时器中断之前。
Oh yeah,
是的,
the thread, the thread yields the CPU,
线程让出 CPU ，
there's the exec exec yields the CPU,
exec 让出 CPU ，
so there's actually many points,
所以实际上有很多点，
that even though I've been driving this discussion with a timer interrupt,
尽管我一直在用定时器中断来讨论，
in fact, in almost almost all cases
事实上，在几乎所有的情况下，
where xv6 switches between threads,
xv6 在线程之间切换，
it's not due to timer interrupts,
不是由于定时器中断，
it's because some system calls waiting for something
因为有些系统调用在等待某些东西，
or decides that it needs to give up the CPU
决定需要放弃 CPU ，
and so for example exec does various things
比如， exec 执行各种操作，
and then calls yield to give up the CPU
然后调用 yield 并放弃 CPU ，
and it does that, there's really nothing,
它就是这么做的，
does that independently of whether there's timer interrupt.
独立去做，与定时器中断无关。
Yes.
是的。
All right, the time is up for this lecture,
好了，这节课的时间到了，
I think I'll continue some of this discussion next week,
我想下周我会继续讨论这个问题，
but I'm happy to take more questions right now,
但是我现在很乐意回答更多的问题，
if people have them.
如果人们有问题的话。
So let's say the operating system,
那么，让我们说操作系统，
actually I takes on a the thread implementation,
实际上，我采用了线程实现，
so so for example you want to run multiple threads of a process on multiple CPUs,
比如，你希望在多个 CPU 上运行一个进程的多个线程，
like that has to be handled by the OS,
这必须由操作系统来处理，
that cannot just be handled in user space, right?
不能在用户空间中处理，是吗？
How does that kind of switching work
这种切换是怎么工作的，
is each, each thread now becomes the same as a process,
是每个线程都变成了一个进程，
like is always going to loop through all existing threads
比如，在所有现有线程中循环，
or you know because like each CPU will still switch between,
或者，因为每个 CPU 仍然会切换，
even if one process give eight cores,
即使一个进程提供八个核心，
like it's still gonna switch switch each of the CPUs between those
它还会在这些 CPU 之间切换，
and a couple of other processes
以及其他一些进程，
and also we don't want to really
而且我们也不想，在同一个 CPU 上的切换一个线程和另一个线程，
or do we, I don't know.
或者我们希望，我不知道。
Wait, can I.
等等，我能不能。
I'm not sure what the question is.
我不确定问题是什么。
Yeah, I guess I guess,
是的，我想，
can you just explain more like how does that happen.
你能解释一下这是怎么发生的吗？
Sorry, how does what happened.
抱歉，什么是怎么发生的。
Let's say we have multiple threads per process,
假设每个进程有多个线程，
so that they can and they can run on different CPUs,
它们可以在不同的 CPU 上运行，
like how do we go, how do you go about there.
我们如何处理这些。
So Linux, for example supports multiple threads per process
比如， Linux 支持每个进程多个线程，
and in Linux, the implementation, it's a complex implementation,
在 Linux 中，是一个很复杂的实现，
but maybe the simplest way to explain it is that,
也许最简单的解释是，
each, it's almost as if each thread in Linux is a complete process,
几乎 Linux 中的每个线程都是一个完整的进程，
and the the threads of a given,
给定进程的线程，
what we would call the threads of a particular process
我们称之为特定进程的线程，
are essentially separate processes that share the same memory,
本质上是共享内存的独立进程，
so Linux has sort of separated out the notion of thread of execution from address space
所以 Linux 在某种程度上将执行线程的概念从地址空间中分离出来，
and you know you can have them separately,
你可以把它们独立起来，
and if you make two threads in one process,
如果在一个进程中有两个线程，
it basically makes two processes that share one address space,
它基本上是两个进程共享一个地址空间，
and then from then on,
从那时起，
the scheduling is not unlike what xv6 does for individual processes.
调度与 xv6 对各个进程所做的没有什么不同。
I see and then is there anything,
我明白了，然后，有没有什么东西，
like does the user have to specify,
比如用户必须指定，
like okay pin each thread to a CPU
每个线程要固定到一个 CPU 上，
or how does the OS make sure
或者操作系统如何确保
that different threads of the same process don't run on the same core,
同一进程的不同线程不会在同一核心上运行，
because that's kind of defeating the purpose,
因为这是不是违反了目的，
or not, I guess, I don't know.
或者不是，我猜的，我不知道。
The the, it's actually just like it's much like xv6, namely the,
这个其实跟 xv6 很像，就是，
you know there's four cores
这里有四个核心，
and Linux will just find four things for one of those four cores,
Linux 只会为这四个核心中找到四个东西，
they maybe, you know if there's not much going on,
如果没有太多的事情发生，
then maybe they'll be four threads of the same process,
那么可能会是同一进程的四个线程，
or if there's a hundred users logged in on Athena machine,
或者如果有一百个用户登录到 Athena 机器，
maybe it's one thread each from multiple different processes,
也许是每个线程来自多个不同的进程，
you know, there's not any one answer
没有一个固定答案，
or the kernel basically find something for each core to do
或者内核为每个核心找到要做的事情，
and then that core does that thing.
然后那个核心做那件事。
Okay, that makes sense.
好的，理解了。
You can, you know if you're if you want to do careful measurements,
如果你想仔细测量，
there is a way to pin threads to cores,
有一种方法可以将线程固定在核心上，
but people only do it when they're up to something strange.
但是人们只有在做一些奇怪的事情时才会这么做。
So you share the virtual table.
所以是共享虚拟表。
Can you say it again.
你能再说一遍吗？
Virtual memory.
虚拟内存。
So they say they have the same page table, those threads.
所以说哪些线程有相同的页表。
Yeah yeah, if you're on Linux, if you create two threads in one process,
是的，如果你在 Linux 上，在一个进程中创建两个线程，
then you have these two threads.
然后你就有了两个线程。
I don't know if they like literally share the exact same page table
我不知道它们是否共享完全相同的页表，
or whether their page tables are identical,
或者它们的页表是相同的，
one or the other.
两个中的一个。
Is there a reason why they would have to be separate, ever,
有没有原因让它们分开，
if you manually map memory, or.
如果你手动映射内存，或者。
I I don't know enough to know whether which which Linux does.
我不知道 Linux 是哪种。
Okay, I have another question about a small detail,
好的，我还有一个关于一个小细节的问题，
so basically like from my understanding when you call swtch,
根据我的理解，当你调用 swtch 时，
you switch from one call to switch to another,
从一个调用切换到另一个，
so the first time you call swtch,
所以当你第一次调用 swtch 时，
you have to like kind of artificially create other endpoint to come back to, right.
必须人为地创建返回的端点，是吧。
Yes.
是的。
Because you can't just randomly jump in to [] any code.
因为你不能随便跳到任何代码。
Yes, you want to know where that, where that fake,
是的，你想知道那个伪造在哪里，
where that context was cooked up.
那个上下文是在哪里创造的。
Probably somewhere where the process is created, I guess,
我猜可能是在进程创建的地方，
I don't know.
我不知道。
Yeah yeah, maybe userinit,
是的，可能是 userinit ，
or not using allocproc.
没有使用 allocproc 。
I don't know.
我也不知道。
There's something called fork trap or something.
有一个叫做 fork trap 的东西。
Yeah, look at this, yeah we got forkret,
是的，看这个，有 forkret ，
okay so an allocproc
好的，所以 allocproc ，
which is called both for the very first process at boot time and by fork,
在引导时的第一个进程或 fork 时调用，
allocproc sets up the critical elements of the context for the new processes,
allocproc 为新进程设置上下文的关键元素，
it, it sets up the new process's context,
它设置了新进程的上下文，
it actually doesn't matter what most of the registers are,
大多数寄存器是什么并不重要，
but it does matter what ra is,
但重要的是 ra 是什么，
because that's where the swtch the very first swtch
因为第一个 swtch ，
and that process is going to return to ra,
那个进程会返回到 ra ，
And that process is going to need to use its own stack,
那个进程需要使用自己的堆栈，
so ra and sp setup, faked essentially,
所以 ra 和 sp 设置，是伪造的，
so the very first swtch or process works.
所以，第一个 swtch 或进程可以正常工作。
So, so if I understand this correctly,
所以，如果我理解正确的话，
when this swtch will happen,
当这个 swtch 发生时，
then it'll basically just start executing the first instruction inside of the forkret,
它会开始执行 forkret 内部的第一条指令，
as if forkret just called swtch and return from.
forkret 调用 swtch ，再返回。
Yeah yeah, the return from switch is gonna be jump to the beginning of forkret.
是的，从 swtch 返回跳到 forkret 的开头。
Alright, interesting,
好的，有意思，
do we ever call forkret or is it always happens,
我们有没有调用 forkret ，还是总是这样，
I think it always happens like this.
我想总是这样发生的。
I don't think anything ever calls forkret for [],
我不认为有什么东西调用了 forkret ，
because just,
因为，
yeah it's only executed in this weird way from first [] process is run.
是的，它只在第一个进程运行时以这种奇怪的方式执行。
It is really its job is to release the lock the scheduler took
它的工作实际上是释放调度器占用的锁，
and then return
然后返回，
and then this usertrapret, of course, is also fake.
然后这个 usertrapret ，当然，也是伪造的。
That it's, it's,
它是，
yeah it's like it's as if returning from a trap,
就像是从 trap 返回，
except the trapframe is faked also,
trapframe 也是伪造的，
to to have like jump to the first instruction in the user code.
调到用户代码的第一个指令。
Oh, but the trapframe,
但是 trapframe ，
it's again the same like you don't need to initialize any registers,
它又是一样，不需要初始化任何寄存器，
because it's like well we're going to the beginning,
因为就像我们要从头开始，
so you don't need to assume anything.
所以你不需要假设任何事。
Yeah, the program counter I think is.
是的，程序计数器我认为是。
Yeah.
是的。
It needs to be initialized to zero,
它需要初始化为零，
I don't know what else,
我不知道还有什么，
you maybe maybe it.
也许就是它。
They probably if we call them it doesn't right,
它们可能，如果我们调用它们不正确，
because if we already do the call,
因为如果我们已经进行了调用，
then that's going to set the program counter.
那么就会设置程序计数器。
Yeah, so here's this only happens,
是的，只会在这里发生，
because fork copies, fork copies the program counter,
是因为 fork 复制了程序计数器，
the user program counter
用户程序计数器，
and so the only time when we're not doing fork is
所以我们唯一不做 fork 的是，
for the very first process
对于第一个进程，
where it's like explicitly deceptive.
在那里它明显的欺骗性的。
Oh.
噢。
And stack pointer.
而且堆栈指针。
Oh yeah.
哦，是的。
Also needs to be set up.
也需要设置。
Oh yeah, because it's that EPC that's not PC,
是的，因为它是 EPC 不是 PC ，
that's the one that's gonna get swapped by the trap trampoline.
就是那个要被 trampoline 换掉的。
Yes.
是的。
Oh, I see.
哦，我明白了。
Because the real PC is actually gonna be in trap like inside trampoline,
因为真正的程序计数器会在 trampoline 中，
but then we're gonna switch it to jump to there.
但是我们要把它切换，跳到那里。
Yeah.
是的。
Can I just ask,
我能不能问一下，
like can you go back to the allocproc.
你能不能回到 allocproc 。
I think there's,
我觉得这里，
oh no sorry, forkret
哦，不是，抱歉，是 forkret ，
there is something there, that happens I think for the first process only.
那里有一些东西我想只发生在第一个进程。
What's this for a first call, I wasn't really sure what happened.
对于第一个调用，我不太确定发生了什么事。
Let's see,
我们看看，
the file system, the file system needs to be initialized
文件系统需要初始化，
and in particular some stuff needs to be read off the disk
特别是一些内容需要从磁盘上读取，
in order to get the file system going,
为了使文件系统运行，
like there's this thing called the super block,
比如有一种叫做超级块，
which describes how big the file system are,
用来描述文件系统有多大，
and where the various things are in the file system
以及文件系统中各种内容的位置，
and there's also a crash recovery log,
还有一个崩溃恢复日志，
that needs to be replayed
需要重播，
in order to recover from a previous crash,
以便从之前的崩溃中恢复过来，
if there was one.
如果有的话。
But in order to do anything in the file system,
但是为了在文件系统中执行任何操作，
you need to be able to wait for disk operations to complete,
你需要等待磁盘操作完成，
but the way xv6 works,
但是 xv6 的工作方式，
you really can only execute the file system code in the context of process,
你只能在进程的上下文中执行文件系统代码，
in order to like wait for IO
为了比如等待 IO ，
and so therefore the initialization of the file system has to be deferred
所以文件系统的初始化必须推迟，
until the first time we have a process running.
直到我们有一个进程在运行。
And that occurs in the very first process in forkret.
这发生在 forkret 的第一个进程中。
I see.
我明白了。
And I'm guessing we'll learn more about this later.
我猜我们稍后会对此有更多了解。
Yeah, not about this horrible mess,
是的，不是关于这个烂摊子，
but about how file systems work.
而是关于文件系统是如何工作的。
All right okay well, thank you,
好的，谢谢，
I'm sorry for holding on so long.
抱歉占用您时间了。
Thanks for all the answers.
谢谢你的回答。
Sorry, it that init that process,
抱歉，是不是在初始化个进程，
when this thing is executed ...
当这个东西被执行的时候……